Evening, miss!
Malam, Neng Sari!
Evening, sir!
Malam, Kang Cecep.
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak!
Kang Mak!
Fall in!
Maju, Semua! Maju!
Watch out, it's a grenade!
Awas granat!
Oh, my unfortunate destiny
Nasib, ya, nasib
When I was born I was colonized by the Dutch
Ketika lahir dijajah Belanda
When I was little I was colonized by Japanese
Di kala kecil, dijajah Jepang
When I grew up
Saat dewasa
I was sent to war
Aku dikirim berperang
What song is that?
Nyanyi apaan sih?
Oh, my unfortunate destiny
Nasib, ya, nasib
Now, I'm just waiting
Sekarang aku hanya menunggu
For my death
Ajal menjemputku
Why did your voice get louder?
Kenapa suaramu makin keras?
- Oh, my destiny… - Shut up!
- Nasib, ya… - Hei! Sudah, diam!
Solah.
Solah.
He sang louder so that you'll hear him.
Dia menyanyi makin keras biar kau dengar.
I know my hearing is impaired,
Eh, gue budek, tapi enggak budek-budek banget, ya!
- You're deaf, Solah! - No, I can still hear!
Kau budek, Solah!
- What did you say? - See?
- Apaan? - Nah, kan?
You're deaf, Solah!
Kau budek, Solah!
You didn't say anything!
Kayaknya lo enggak ngomong!
Fine, how about you try singing?
Udah, kau aja yang nyanyi, bisa enggak?
- Fine, I will. - Good!
- Ya udah, biar gue yang nyanyi. - Iya!
- To boost our morale. - Correct!
- Biar kita bersemangat. - Betul!
Come on, guys!
- Ayo semua, Teman-Teman! - Ayo!
If you're happy and you know it Clap your hands!
Kalau kau suka hati, tepuk tangan!
Let's sing another song.
Ganti lagu.
Quiet!
Berisik, tahu?
Do you think we're on a picnic?
Kalian pikir kita piknik di sini?
Are you happy being sent to war from morning until night?
Senang dikirim berperang dari pagi sampai malam kayak gini?
What should we do to boost our morale?
Terus ngapain biar semangat?
I think now is not the time to sing.
Saya rasa sekarang bukan saatnya untuk nyanyi-nyanyi.
It's time for us to rise and fight!
Sudah saatnya kita bangkit dan melawan!
Let's show them that they can't trample over us!
Kita tunjukkan kalau kita bukan bangsa yang mudah diinjak-injak seenaknya!
Whatever wounds we experience now
Luka apa pun yang kita alami sekarang,
won't stop us from fighting
tidak akan menghentikan kita untuk terus berjuang
to make our country proud!
menyatukan Indonesia.
Fight!
Majulah kalian!
Get out there! Raise your weapons!
Keluar kalian dari sini! Angkat senjata kalian!
Are you not coming?
Abang enggak ikut?
You're all still young.
Ya, kalian kan masih muda.
You should be at the front. An old man like me will support you
Kalian maju di depan. Yang tua bisa dukung dari belakang.
With prayers.
Sambil doa.
On the battlefield, age doesn't matter!
Enggak ada tua-muda kalau di medan perang!
If we want to advance, we'll do it together!
Kalau mau terus maju, ya sama-sama!
Why are you copying me?
Kok sama-sama?
Enough!
Sudah, cukup!
If none of you wants to go, I'll go by myself!
Kalau kalian pada enggak mau maju, biar saya yang maju sendirian!
It's okay! I know I'm a scaredy-cat,
Enggak apa-apa.
I have to go home to my wife, Sari.
Saya itu harus pulang, ketemu istri saya, si Sari.
She must have already given birth.
Dia pasti sudah melahirkan anak kami.
Don't you miss your family?
Kalian memang tidak kangen sama keluarga?
You do, don't you?
Kangen, kan?
That's why we have to move forward without fear!
Makanya kita harus maju tak gentar!
Stand up for what's right!
Membela yang benar!
Move forward without fear!
Maju tak gentar!
Our rights are invaded!
Hak kita ini diserang!
Move together,
Maju serentak,
banish the attackers!
mengusir penyerang!
we will surely win!
tentu kita menang!
Cool!
Keren.
You're so cool.
Keren, Makmur.
No! What do you mean cool?
Enggak! Keren dari mana?
Those were song lyrics.
Itu kayaknya lirik lagu, deh.
What lyrics?
Lirik apaan, Kang?
Take it from the top.
Coba ulang dari awal.
If none of you wants to go,
Kalau kalian tidak ada yang mau maju,
I'll go by myself, I don't mind!
biar saya yang maju sendirian. Enggak apa-apa!
From the "move forward."
Yang "Maju tak"-nya aja.
Not that part, start from the "move forward."
"Maju tak"-nya langsung, enggak dari awal.
No.
- Enggak usah. - Enggak.
Repeat the "move forward" part!
Mak, ulangin sekali lagi yang "Maju tak"-nya doang.
I don't appreciate you forcing me.
Saya enggak suka dipaksa, Kang.
Everyone, stop!
Udah, berhenti semua!
It's not the time for us to play around!
Bukan waktunya kita main-main lagi.
It's time to show
Sudah saatnya kita tunjukkan siapa kita!
True soldiers!
Tentara sejati!
Yessir!
Siap, dong!
Good morning, noon, and night
Selamat pagi, siang, malam
We are true soldiers!
Kami tentara sejati
Soldiers of this land
Pasukan bumi pertiwi
Fighting for our country!
Berjuang demi negeri
This is our spirit!
Ini jiwa kami
Forever brothers, in life and death!
Selamanya, saudara Sehidup, semati
Indonesia!
Indonesia!
Kang Mak!
Kang Mak!
- Son! Let's get inside! - Why, Dad?
- Ayo masuk, Nak! - Kenapa, Pak?
Don't ask! Just get in!
Jangan banyak tanya. Masuk.
- Come on! - Kang Mak!
- Ayo, Nak! Kita masuk. - Kang Mak!
Close the doors and windows!
Tutup!
Our child is born, honey.
Anak kita udah lahir, Kang.
At this rate, we'll die soon!
Kalau begini, kita bisa mati!
Dear God,
Ya, Tuhan,
please don't take my life.
jangan ambil nyawa saya, ya, Tuhan.
I have to live.
Pokoknya saya harus hidup.
Whatever happens, I need to see my wife and child.
Apa pun yang terjadi, saya harus ketemu sama istri dan anak saya, ya, Tuhan.
Please, God!
Tolong, ya, Tuhan.
Don't talk about death.
Jangan ngomongin mati.
That's taboo.
Pantang.
- We're still alive! - If Makmur doesn't want to die,
Kita masih hidup.
then, we can't die.
kita juga enggak boleh mati!
If that's the case, none of us can die.
Kalau begitu, kita enggak boleh ada yang mati!
We have to stay alive!
Kita semua harus hidup!
True soldiers!
Tentara sejati!
Attack!
Serang!
Retreat!
Mundur!
Sari…
Sari…
Sari!
Sari!
Go to sleep, my dear child
Tidur, Anakku Sayang
Mom is here, waiting
Mami Sari di sini menanti
For your father, Makmur
Papi Makmur akan datang
Mom, I'm scared.
Ibu, takut.
Together again
Bersama kita lagi
Your father, Makmur
Papi Makmur akan datang
Solah.
Solah!
We're alive.
Kita selamat!
I'm coming home, honey!
Akang pulang, Neng! Akang pulang!
Since my village is the closest, let's go to Fajrul's village first.
Kampung saya paling dekat,
After that, we'll go to Solah's village.
Setelah kampung Kang Fajrul, baru ke kampung Kang Solah.
Then, to Jaka's village.
Baru ke kampungnya Kang Jaka.
His village is near Solah's.
Karena kampungnya Kang Jaka dekat dengan Kang Solah.
Since Supra's village is the farthest, we'll go to his village next.
Karena kampungnya Kang Supra paling jauh, berikutnya Kang Supra.
Lastly…
Nah, terakhir, sa…
If I go last, Sari will be waiting too long. It's been months.
Kalau saya terakhir, kasihan Sari. Dia udah nunggu berbulan-bulan.
If we use your plan, we'll be sailing two months.
Kalau begitu, kita dua bulan di perahu. Udah, ikutin caraku.
First,
Pertama, kita ke kampungnya Makmur yang paling dekat.
Second, my village.
Kedua, ke kampungku.
Then, Solah's village. After that, Jaka's village.
Baru ke kampungnya Solah.
Lastly, we'll go to Supra's village since it's the farthest.
Nah, terakhir, karena paling jauh, kampung Bang Supra.
It's not far enough.
Ya, kalau itu kurang jauh.
Here?
Sini?
It's not far enough!
Kurang jauh!
There.
Nah.
Now that's what I'm talking about. Supra's village is that far!
Kampungnya Bang Supra itu di sana! Kan jauh emang.
Why did you do it?
Kok dibuang?
I'm just showing you how far his village is.
Itu kampungnya Bang Supra, buat patokan.
My canteen?
Botol minumku.
- Right.
- Oh, iya. - Iya.
Right, it's your canteen.
Iya, botol minum, ya.
If one person is dehydrated, everyone should also be.
Satu dehidrasi, semua dehidrasi ya.
- Come on, let's go! - I'm so thirsty.
- Ayo, berangkat. - Haus banget gue.
It's gonna be so hot.
Panas pasti di perjalanan.
- Sir, let's go! - Let's go!
- Mang! Jalan, Mang. - Mang! Jalan, Mang!
It'll already be dark when we reach my village.
Kelihatannya sih kalau sampe rumah saya, sudah gelap.
How about you stop by and eat?
Nanti istirahat aja dulu, ya? Makan dulu.
Sari is a great cook!
Si Sari itu kalau masak, aduh, enak.
Great! It's been so long since we've had a proper meal.
Pas banget. Udah lama kita enggak makan enak.
- Can she cook fried catfish? - Of course!
- Dia bisa masak pecel lele, enggak? - Bisa!
Grilled fish with torch ginger?
Kalau ikan bakar kecombrang?
That's a piece of cake, Fajrul!
Itu mah gampang, Kang Fajrul.
Can she make pepes?
Kalau pepes-pepesan, bisa enggak?
Tofu pepes, fish pepes, squid pepes, you name it!
Segala pepes bisa! Pepes tahu, pepes ikan, pepes cumi.
- Which one do you like? - I like goat pepes.
- Pepes apa? - Pepes kambing, saya mah.
That's gonna be a big pepes. What leaf should we use to wrap it?
Pepes kambing mah gede! Bungkusnya pakai daun apa?
- Banana leaves, of course. - Pardon me, Fajrul.
- Ya daun pisang, Mur. - Kang Fajrul, maaf.
A banana leaf is this big, right? We're talking about a goat!
Daun pisang paling segimana? Segini.
We have to cut up the goat, of course!
Kambingnya kau potong-potong.
Enough! How about this?
Ya udah! Ini aja saya mah, gampang.
Sunny side up egg with sambal.
Telur mata sapi pakai sambal.
Sir.
Kang.
Making goat pepes is hard enough, cow even more so!
Kambing aja sulit, apalagi sapi yang lebih gede.
You must be joking.
Aduh, Kang Supra bercanda.
Is this your village?
Ini kampung kau, Mur?
It's so quiet here.
Sepi sekali.
If it's crowded, it's called Rambutan Village.
Ya, kalau ramai Kampung Rambutan namanya, Kang.
Where's your house?
Rumahmu di mana?
Still farther in.
Rumah saya masih jauh ke dalam.
But, it is unusually quiet.
Tapi tumben ini memang agak sepi.
Kids used to play around here.
Biasanya ramai anak-anak kecil di sini main.
We're finally here.
Akhirnya sampai juga.
Come on.
Ayo, Kang.
Watch your step.
Yuk. Hati-hati turunnya.
- Let's go. - Okay.
- Ayo, Kang! - Ayo.
Thank you, sir.
Makasih, Bang.
- Solah, is everything okay? - Yes.
- Kang Solah, aman? - Aman!
Honey!
Neng!
I'm home!
Akang pulang, Neng!
Honey!
Neng!
Scary!
Pahit, pahit.
Sari?
Sari!
I'm home, honey!
Akang pulang, Neng!
Honey?
Neng!
Hey!
Hei!
Sir!
Bang!
Boatman!
Perahu!
- Hey! - What is it?
- Heh! - Apa sih?
The boatman just left. He looked scared.
Itu tukang perahunya kabur! Ketakutan!
Look!
Tuh!
Hey!
Hei!
Are we stuck here?
Yah, masa kita kejebak di sini?
Sari?
Sari?
Oh, Sari!
Oh, Sari!
Honey?
Neng?
Sari!
Sari!
Kang Mak!
Kang Mak!
I missed you so much, honey.
Akang kangen banget sama Eneng.
I didn't think you'd ever come back.
Eneng pikir Akang enggak akan pulang ke sini lagi, Kang.
Of course not, honey.
Enggak mungkin, Neng.
I promised you.
Akang kan udah janji.
I will come home.
Akang pasti pulang.
Kang Mak!
Kang Mak!
What is it, honey?
Kenapa, Kang?
I got shot.
Ini luka bekas ketembak.
See. But, I'm fine.
Tuh. Tapi enggak apa-apa.
It's already been treated.
Udah diobatin.
Your hand as well?
Ini tangannya juga?
It was grazed by a bullet, it's not a big deal.
Kalau ini mah cuma keserempet peluru.
I also have wounds on the back.
Di belakang juga masih ada, Neng.
There's one from a grenade. I also got hacked, stabbed.
Ada luka bekas kena granat, dibacok, luka ketusuk.
Oh, honey!
Aduh, Akang!
I'm fine, honey.
Enggak apa-apa, Neng.
- Are you sure? - Yes.
- Enggak apa-apa, benar? - Benar.
For the sake of our country,
Demi bangsa dan negara,
these wounds aren't a big deal.
semua luka itu tidak masalah.
Must be nice to have a wife.
Enak juga, ya, kalau punya istri.
If I had a wife waiting for me at home,
Iya, ya. Gue juga kalau punya istri,
Supra knows a thing or two about that.
Biasanya kalau yang begitu, Bang Supra.
Well, I've been married for a while.
Kalau kita kan memang sudah pengalaman. Romantis.
When I come home, I grab a hold of her head.
Baru pulang, bini kita pegang kepalanya.
Face to face.
Semua. Muka beradu muka.
I'll lick everything.
Terus gue jilatin.
Then, I'll squeeze her.
Gue remas-remas.
Then, I'll lick her from the top of her head…
Terus gue jilatin dari atas kepala…
Then, I'll suck her toes.
Jempol kaki kita cucup.
Enough!
Udah, Bang!
Honey, your stomach.
Neng, perutnya…
Why is it flat?
Kok kempes?
Did you have a miscarriage?
Eneng keguguran?
No!
Tidak!
Honey, our child's right there.
Kang, itu anak kita!
My baby!
Anakku sayang!
She's got a beautiful face like you, Sari.
Wajahnya cantik seperti wajahmu, Sari.
Her eyes are as beautiful as those of a fallen angel's.
Matanya indah, bagai mata bidadari yang turun dari kahyangan.
Our child is a boy, honey.
Anak kita laki-laki, Kang.
I knew it. He's manly like me.
Pantas gagah dan macho ini mah kayak Akang.
I'm your dad, baby.
Ini Papi, Sayang.
I'm Daddy Makmur.
Papi Makmur!
You can call me…
Kamu bisa panggil…
Pih Mak.
Pih Mak.
What's his name, honey?
Siapa nama jagoan kita, Neng?
The name that you've always dreamed of.
Nama yang Akang selalu impi-impikan.
Cipluk?
Cipluk?
His name is Cipluk!
Namanya Cipluk!
I thought it would be Maxim, or Onadio, or Vino.
Kirain namanya Maxim, Onadio, Vino.
It's like a sound.
Kayak bunyi-bunyian.
If he has a brother, it will be more like a sound.
Nanti adiknya lebih kayak bunyi lagi.
Like what?
Apa tuh?
If he has another sibling, the name will be Mak Grompyang.
Kalau punya adik lagi, namanya Mak Grompyang!
Bunch of hicks!
Kampung!
- You're one to talk. Your name is Solah. - Solah is my first name.
Ngaca! Namamu Solah!
My full name is Solah Vicenzio.
Nama belakang gue dong. Solah Vicenzio.
Supra is more of a hick's name!
Hei, nama kampung itu "Supra"!
Don't look at my first name, look at my last name.
Jangan lihat depannya. Lihat belakangnya.
Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Supratman Hatta.
Dengar. Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Supratman Hatta.
That's a great name.
Itu baru nama!
Wait a minute. I think we know those names.
Bentar, Bang. Nama-nama itu kayaknya kita tahu.
Say it one more time.
- Coba ulang sekali lagi. - Iya.
Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Gatot Subroto Hatta.
Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Gatot Subroto Hatta.
Now you have "Gatot Subroto"?
- Sekarang ada "Gatot Subroto"-nya. - Dari tadi!
No, it was "Supratman."
Enggak ada, Bang. Tadi "Supratman"!
Guys!
Teman-teman.
Meet my wife, Sari.
Kenalin, ini istri saya yang suka saya ceritain. Sari.
I'm Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Gatot Subroto Sudirman Hatta!
Saya Supra Widodo Cokroaminoto Gatot Subroto Sudirman Hatta!
- You missed the "Supratman". - "Sudirman" now?
- "Supratman"-nya hilang! - Ganti "Sudirman"?
What's with you guys? It's my full name.
Kenapa sih? Memang nama panjangnya begitu.
You keep changing it.
Tapi ganti-ganti mulu!
Oh, shut up!
Ribet amat.
I'm Jaka.
Saya Jaka.
I helped Makmur when he got shot.
Saya yang nolongin Makmur waktu ketembak.
I'm Fajrul.
Saya Fajrul.
I always reminded Makmur to stay faithful.
Saya yang selalu ngingetin Makmur untuk tetap setia.
There were many temptations on the battlefield.
Walaupun di medan perang banyak godaan.
What kind of temptations? Being kissed by a bomb?
Godaan apaan di medan perang? Kecium bom?
Hi, Sari.
Hai, Sari.
I'm…
Saya…
Solah Vicenzio.
Solah Vicenzio.
Do you possibly have a sister?
Apakah kamu memiliki saudara perempuan?
No, I'm an only child.
Enggak, Kang. Saya anak tunggal.
Best friend?
Sahabat?
Or anyone who's as pretty as you?
Siapa pun yang cantiknya kayak kamu, gitu. Ada enggak?
There aren't any, Solah.
Enggak ada, Kang Solah.
Sari is the prettiest woman in the village.
Sari ini wanita paling cantik di kampung sini.
When there's a competition, she always wins.
Makanya kalau ada perlombaan, selalu juara.
Sari once won the Charm of the Village competition.
Sari itu pernah juara Pesona Wajah Kampung.
She was also the favorite contender in the Village Flower.
Pernah juara favorit Kembang Kampung.
She was also the winner of the Dreamy Market Princess competition.
Pernah juga juara Putri Pasar Idaman.
She's won every single beauty pageant in this village.
Pokoknya mah juara umum dari semua
She is the best of the best.
Malah yang terakhir ini yang terbaik.
She won the River Princess competition for three years straight.
Pernah juara tiga tahun berturut-turut Putri Sungai.
Amazing achievements!
Luar biasa.
Thank you, Solah.
Terima kasih, Kang Solah.
Anyway, I have an announcement to make.
Nah, sekalian nih, saya mau ngumumin.
Now, I'm officially a father because our child is born.
Kalau sekarang, saya sudah resmi menjadi Papi.
His name is amazing.
Namanya luar biasa.
Cipluk.
Cipluk.
His full name is Cipluk Makmur Sari.
Nama panjangnya Cipluk Makmur Sari.
I see. Just like a hardware store.
Iya. Kayak toko bangunan.
Furniture.
Mebel.
Don't be like that.
Enggak boleh begitu.
Cipluk is a beautiful name.
Cipluk adalah nama yang sangat indah.
Cipluk has to remember his name until he's old.
Cipluk harus selalu mengingat namanya sampai dia tua nanti.
He must never forget his full name.
Jangan sampai begitu dia tua, dia lupa sama nama panjangnya.
What?
Apa?
Makmur!
Makmur!
The boatman left. He looked scared.
Tukang perahunya tadi kabur. Ketakutan.
Now, we can't go home.
Kita enggak bisa pulang.
Why don't you guys stay here for the night?
Sekalian saja nginep di sini, ya?
You said you wanted to try Sari's cooking!
Katanya mau nyobain makanan Sari.
Across the river over there
Kebetulan, di seberang sungai sana,
is my aunt's house. It's vacant for some time.
ada rumah Uwak saya yang sudah lama kosong.
So, you can stay there.
Nah, jadi teman-teman semua bisa nginep di situ.
I agree. We will stay there.
Oke, setuju! Kita nginep dulu di situ.
You said you didn't want to stay.
Katanya enggak mau nginep di sini.
He offered us, how can we decline?
Kan ditawarin. Masa mau ditolak?
Besides, how can we go home?
Lagian, mau pulang naik apaan?
The boat already left. Swimming?
Perahunya udah pergi. Mau berenang?
Sari.
Sari.
My friends and I
Saya dan teman-teman
want to show our utmost gratitude.
mengucapkan terima kasih.
And… I love you, Sari.
Dan…
- What did you say? - I love you, Makmur!
Apa tadi?
- You said Sari earlier. - I love you, Sari, Makmur's wife.
- Tadi Sari. - Enggak, tadi Sari.
Are you going to steal her?
Mau ngerebut?
No! I love you Sari, I love you Makmur,
Bukan! Aku cinta Sari. Aku cinta Makmur.
I love you Cipluk and everybody!
Aku cinta Cipluk!
You want to steal your friend's wife?
- Mau rebut istri teman? - Bukan.
I'm not stealing her!
- Siapa yang mau rebut? - Ya?
Enough!
Cukup!
It's not the time to be bickering.
Bukan saatnya kita untuk berdebat.
Tomorrow, we'll go to the market.
Besok kita ke pasar, ya!
Sari will cook delicious dishes for us!
Sari mau masak enak buat kita semua!
- All right! - Ali right, Mur!
- Siap! - Siap, Mur!
Come on, honey.
Ayo, Neng.
I always prayed for your safety.
Eneng selalu doain Akang supaya Akang selamat.
Your prayer made me strong when I was fighting in the war.
Itu artinya doa Eneng
I can't imagine
Eneng enggak bisa bayangin,
if you had died on the battlefield.
kalau Akang mati di medan perang.
If I die first,
Kalau Akang sampai mati duluan,
I will become a ghost and come back.
Akang pasti akan kembali sebagai setan…
To meet you and Cipluk.
…untuk menemui Eneng sama Cipluk.
Stop it, I'm scared.
Akang! Seram.
You're scared, aren't you?
Takut, ya, Neng?
But, honey,
Tapi, Kang,
what if…
kalau Eneng…
I'm the one who died while waiting
yang mati saat nunggu Akang di sini,
for you here?
gimana?
I'm grateful that didn't happen.
Akang mah bersyukur itu enggak pernah terjadi.
Look at us now.
Lihat sekarang.
We're together, just like old times.
Kita udah sama-sama lagi kayak dulu.
But now, there are three of us.
Tapi bedanya, sekarang kita udah bertiga.
We have Cipluk.
Ada Cipluk.
Maybe there'll be four of us, or five, twelve,
Mungkin besok berempat, berlima, berduabelas,
- a hundred… - Come on, how can there be that many?
- seratus, seribu… - Masa banyak banget, Akang?
To light up the house, honey!
Ya, biar rumahnya ramai, Neng.
So, it won't be quiet.
Biar enggak sepi.
What is it?
Kenapa lagi ini?
I'm scared, honey.
Eneng takut, Kang.
What are you scared of?
Takut apa?
I'm scared of us getting separated again.
Takut kalau kita berpisah lagi.
Honey.
Neng.
You have to trust me.
Eneng harus percaya sama Akang.
I will never leave you again.
Akang enggak akan pernah ninggalin Eneng lagi.
From now on,
Dan mulai sekarang,
we will be together forever.
kita akan sama-sama terus selama-lamanya.
I promise.
Akang janji.
So, don't be scared, okay?
Jadi, Eneng enggak boleh takut, ya?
I'm here.
Ada Akang.
Supra!
Bang! Bang Supra!
- Wake up! - What is it?
- Bangun, Bang! - Apaan?
- What's that shadow? There! - Where?
- Itu bayangan apa, Bang? Itu! - Mana?
It's a bird.
Burung.
What do you mean a bird?
Burung dari mana sih?
- It's a woman. - Fajrul, wake up.
- Perempuan, Bang! - Jrul, bangun.
What?
Apa, Bang?
What shadow is that? A bird or a woman?
Itu bayangan burung apa perempuan?
- It's a dog. - Gosh.
- Anjing, Bang. - Aduh.
A dog?
Anjing?
- It's a woman! - A bird!
- Perempuan! - Burung!
It's obviously a dog.
Itu anjing! Jelas sekali itu anjing!
But, there's a bird, right?
Tapi ada burungnya, kan?
You're all so loud.
Aduh, berisik banget sih!
Aren't you guys tired?
Enggak pada capek apa?
Jaka, look there.
Jak, lo lihat itu.
Is that the shadow of a bird, a dog, or a woman?
Itu bayangan burung, anjing, apa perempuan, Jak?
- It's not a bird. - See?
- Bukan burung. - Kan?
It's not a dog.
Bukan anjing.
See?
Nah, kan?
It's not a woman.
Bukan perempuan.
It's a ghost.
Itu setan.
A ghost?
Setan?
Jaka!
Jaka! Jak!
Try to wake him up.
Kau yang bangunin dia.
Jaka, wake up.
Jaka, bangun.
Ghost!
Setan!
What are you doing?
Ngapain lo pada?
We were tidying things up.
- Ini, mau beberes. - Mau bersih-bersih.
We're in someone's house, we have to tidy things up.
Tinggal di rumah orang enggak enak kalau enggak dibersihin, ya, kan?
- Where's the broom? - My body is aching.
- Sapu mana? - Kenapa badan gue sakit?
- The view was phenomenal, right? - Yes, in the morning.
- Pemandangannya tadi bagus, ya? - Iya! Kalau pagi, ya?
You didn't see it.
Dia enggak lihat.
- What do you call it? Hidden gem. - Yes, hidden gem.
- Ini istilahnya tuh hidden gem. - Iya, hidden gem.
The river was beautiful. The water was calm and cold.
Sungainya bagus, airnya tenang, dingin juga.
If only you didn't wake up late.
Telat bangun sih.
Supra! Solah!
Kang Supra! Kang Solah!
Jaka, Fajrul! Come on, wake up!
Kang Jaka, Kang Fajrul! Ayo bangun!
- Hey, Mur! - Are we still going to the market?
- Iya, Mur! - Jadi enggak, ke pasar?
Of course!
Siap! Ikut!
Come on, let's freshen up.
Ya udah, yuk siap-siap.
I can't wait to meet Sari again.
Enggak sabar pengen ketemu Sari lagi.
Let's go now. If we go later, everything will be sold out.
Ayo berangkat sekarang.
- You want to try Sari's cooking, right? - Let's go! Where's Sari?
Katanya mau coba masakan Sari!
- She's got Cipluk, so she's not coming. - Okay.
- Sari kan jagain cipluk. Enggak ikut. - Oh, iya.
But it'll be tiring if we have to paddle to the market.
Tapi capek banget kalau ngedayung sampai pasar.
- What should we do? - There's a boatman.
- Terus gimana? - Itu ada tukang dayung.
- Let's ask him to take us there. - That's Mr. Cecep.
- Kita minta anterin aja ke pasar. - Itu Kang Cecep.
Mr. Cecep!
Kang Cecep!
Mr. Cecep, do you remember me?
Kang Cecep, masih ingat saya?
Can you take us to the market?
Minta tolong anterin ke pasar!
- Don't look! - They're not used to paddling.
- Jangan nengok! - Kami kecapekan ngedayung.
Mr. Cecep!
Kang Cecep!
Don't look!
Jangan nengok!
- What's with him? - Don't look!
Gimana sih ini, Kang Cecep?
- Why does he look so scared? - Yes, Mur.
Kok kayak ketakutan gitu, dia?
Well, people used to say that it's haunted around here.
Memang kalau dari dulu sih, di sini terkenal angker.
But, it's an old wives' tale.
Tapi itu cuma mitos.
Come on!
Ayo.
Mr. Wiwid!
Mas Wiwid!
Hey, Makmur is here!
Makmur datang!
- Makmur is here! - Mr. Wiwid, how are you?
- Makmur datang! - Mas Wiwid, apa kabar?
- You're famous here. - I'm glad to know you.
- Kau tenar di kampung ini. - Bangga gue temenan sama lo.
Mr. Wiwid, Sari is going to cook us something special
Mas Wiwid, Sari lagi mau masak yang spesial buat kita,
since we just got back from war.
karena baru pulang dari medan perang.
Do you have any vegetables?
Sayur-sayuran ada?
I do! Tatang, grab the veggies!
Ada! Tatang! Ambilin, Tang!
Over here!
Ayo, sini!
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
- How much is this? - It's free, Makmur!
- Ini berapa harganya? - Gratis, Mas Makmur!
What matters is Sari's happiness.
Yang penting kan Sari bahagia.
Thank you.
Terima kasih!
- I also need spices for these. - I have some.
Saya juga butuh bumbu-bumbu buat makanannya.
Give it to him!
Kasih, Dang!
This is number one.
Enaknya nomor satu ini!
Do you have coffee and sugar?
Kalau kopi sama gula ada?
Of course!
Ada!
How about some papaya?
Kalau pepaya ada, Pak Wiwid?
Yayat! Give it to them.
Yayat! Kasihkan, Yat!
This is number three.
Ini nomor tiga.
Watermelon?
Kalau semangka, ada?
Yati! Where is she? Yati, give it to them!
Yati! Mana Yati? Yati, kasihkan.
This is my fourth wife.
Ini istri saya yang nomor empat.
Do you have any goats?
Kalau kambing?
I do!
Ada!
Give it to them!
Kasih.
Here, sir!
Ini, Bang.
How about a stripper?
Kalau penari telanjang?
Wait a minute.
Sebentar.
Stop! Enough!
Hentikan! Cukup!
I'll give Sari your regards. Thank you, all of you!
Nanti saya sampaikan terima kasih banyak dari Sari, ya,
We'll be going now.
Kita pamit dulu!
Come on.
Ayo.
Let's take a break. I'm still traumatized by that view.
Kita berhenti dulu. Minum dulu, istirahat, ya.
That mesh shirt.
Kaos jaring-jaring.
You shouldn't have asked for it.
Siapa suruh minta?
Mbak Yu Supi!
Eh! Mbah Yu Supi!
So that you'll rest in peace.
Biar kalian tenang.
And have a smooth journey to the afterlife.
Jalan-jalannya sampai ke akhirat.
She's cursing us.
Kita disumpahin ini mah!
Go away.
Jauh-jauh.
Don't haunt us.
Jangan gentayangan!
Haunt? Do you think we're ghosts?
Gentayangan? Emangnya kita setan?
Only ghosts can live with ghosts.
Cuma setan yang bisa tinggal sama setan.
But, who's the ghost?
Iya, tapi siapa yang setan?
Your wife.
Istrimu, Makmur.
Sari is dead.
Si Sari itu sudah mati!
She's a ghost!
Dia itu setan!
If you don't believe me,
Kalau kamu enggak percaya,
look through your crotch, she's a ghost!
intip lewat selangkangan. Sari itu setan!
Why are you laughing?
Kenapa ketawa-ketawa sih?
She's the funniest person in this village.
Mbah Yu Supi itu orang paling lucu di kampung sini.
She says such random things.
Kalau ngomong, suka ngelantur.
Because she's drunk.
Karena mabok!
I see.
Oh, mabok.
But, she's also a shaman.
Tapi dukun juga sih.
Honey, I'm home!
Neng, Akang pulang!
The villagers gave us so much stuff.
Banyak oleh-oleh dari warga kampung!
You can cook straight away.
Jadi, Eneng bisa langsung masak.
Honey, the villagers were so nice.
Neng, orang-orang kampung pada baik semua.
They gave us all of this for free.
Ini semua dikasih gratis.
Did they say anything about me?
Mereka ngomongin tentang Eneng enggak, Kang?
No, what could they possibly say?
Enggak, ngomongin apa?
They just wished you peace. That's all.
Paling cuma ngomong, semoga Eneng bahagia di sana, dapat oleh-oleh.
- Cipluk. - It's okay. You cook, I'll get him.
- Cipluk. - Neng, udah. Biar Akang yang urus.
What do you think about what Mbak Yu Supi said?
Menurut kalian, omongan Mbah Yu Supi gimana?
About Sari? Living with a ghost?
Soal Sari? Tinggal sama setan?
If we think about it, maybe the villagers are scared of us
Ya, kalau dipikir-pikir, bisa aja warga kampung takut sama kita
because we live with a ghost.
karena tinggal sama setan.
What are you saying?
Apaan sih, lo, ngomong diputer-puter?
Are you saying Sari is a ghost?
Menurut lo Sari itu setan?
Ghosts are usually ugly.
Setan tuh biasanya jelek.
Why did you look at me when you said that?
Ngomong jelek kenapa ngeliat ke gue?
No, I looked over there.
- Kagak, ngeliat sana. - Udah enggak usah ribut.
It's easy.
Caranya gampang.
Look through the crotch.
Lihat lewat selangkangan.
Let's just stop bickering. Go, take the goat inside.
Udah! Enggak usah ribut juga.
My waist is hurting.
Eh! Ini pinggang enggak ketahan, sakit.
Jrul!
Jrul, nih.
I need to poop, Solah.
Aku mau berak, Solah.
He's small but he keeps pooping.
Berak mulu badan segede gitu.
Jak!
Jak!
I'm so tired.
Gue enggak, deh. Capek banget.
- I paddled the boat. - So did I!
- Tadi gue habis dayung kapal. - Kan gue juga ngedayung.
- I was in the back… - Enough!
- Tapi kan gue di belakang kayak… - Cukup!
It's not the time to be bickering.
Bukan saatnya berdebat!
Now, pick one. Who will massage me
Sekarang pilih. Siapa yang mau mijit gue,
and who will take the goat?
siapa yang mau bawa kambing?
Jaka, massage me.
Jaka, mijit gue.
Why did you ask us to choose, then?
Ngapain nyuruh milih kalau kayak begitu?
You're already holding the goat. I'd smell like a goat if you massaged me.
Kan lo udah milih bawa kambing. Udah megang.
Just check if she's a ghost or not.
Udah, pokoknya lo pastiin aja Sari itu setan apa bukan.
Check through the crotch.
Cek lewat selangkangan.
What are you doing, Solah?
Kang Solah ngapain?
I'm about to eat the goat. I mean, feed the goat.
Ini, mau makan kambing, eh, mau ngasih makan kambing.
I mean, feed you the goat.
Eh, mau ngasih kambing Sari makan.
I mean, I'm giving you the goat so that you'll cook it for us.
Maksudnya, mau ngasih kambing buat Sari masak, buat kita makan.
Sari.
Sari.
Can you please get some banana leaves?
Tolong, dong. Ambilin daun pisang.
But, why would you need those, right?
Tapi buat apa daun telinga, ya?
I'll go get them.
Solah cari dulu, ya.
If Sari is a ghost, then, that would make their son a ghost too.
Kalau misalnya Sari itu setan,
Of course not.
Ya enggak, lah!
If that's the case, I'm sure Makmur would realize that by now.
Kalau emang begitu, si Makmur udah sadar duluan.
But, the villagers' expressions…
Ya, tapi ekspresi orang-orang, Mang.
What do you mean by ghost?
Siapa yang setan?
No one. The people at the market said it.
Enggak. Di pasar orang pada ngomong.
You believed them?
Terus kalian percaya?
Of course not. How can we?
Ya enggak lah. Gimana bisa percaya?
How can such a cute child be a ghost?
Masa anak selucu ini dibilang anak setan?
You're right, he's cute. Cipluk!
Iya, benar. Lucu banget. Cipluk!
He's so handsome!
Bukan main, ini anak. Cakep banget, ini anak. Tuh, lihat.
- Uncle Jaka! - Cipluk!
- Bang Jaka! - Ciplak, Cipluk!
You're really good with…
Abang emang cocok banget main sama…
With who?
Sama siapa?
What are you guys doing?
Lagi pada ngapain?
Are you learning how to hold Cipluk? Here, hold him.
Kang Supra lagi belajar gendong Cipluk?
Jaka, come with me.
Jaka, temenin gue.
Uncle Supra.
Uwak Supra.
- Damn it! - Damn you!
- Monyet! - Lo yang monyet!
- What are you doing? - I'm pooping.
- Ngapain sih, lo? - Berak.
Don't poop there!
Berak jangan di situ, lah!
Leave me alone, will you?
Ganggu aja.
Hey! That's no different. Go poop by the river!
Hei! Enggak geser gitu doang! Berak di sungai sana!
It's too far!
Kejauhan!
- You're small, you don't need to poop! - Why can't I?
Udah tahu badan segede gitu, pake berak lagi, lo!
Look at you, you're big and you never poop!
Daripada kau! Badan segitu enggak berak!
- None of your business! - When did you last poop?
- Itu bukan urusan lo. - Kapan terakhir berak?
- Yesterday! - Today?
- Kemaren! - Hari ini?
- Not yet! - Let's go.
- Ya, belum. - Ayo.
- What? - Let's have a race.
- Ayo apa? - Balap kita.
No! Why would I have a poop race with you?
Nggak mau! Ngapain gue berak sama lo!
- It smells. You already pooped. - Not yet.
Bau tai! Udah berak lo, ya?
Your mouth smells like poop.
Mulutmu tuh, bau tai.
See, it smells.
Nih, bau tai. Tuh!
I was sure I was holding Cipluk.
Padahal yakin bener si Cipluk yang gue gendong.
I even played with him. I remember his face clearly.
Saya sampai goda-godain! Saya inget banget itu mukanya cipluk!
I know, right? Out of nowhere, it turned into a banana stem.
Makanya. Tiba-tiba jadi gedebong pisang begitu.
Hey!
Hei!
I was looking for you, turns out you're here.
Dicariin, enggak tahunya malah pada di sini.
- Have you checked Sari? - I have.
- Lo udah cek Sari, belum? - Udah.
She's not a ghost.
Aman. Dia mah bukan setan.
- Are you sure? - I'm sure.
- Yakin lo, Lah? - Yakin, Mang.
What is it?
Kenapa sih?
He's such a nuisance.
Ganggu aja, Solah.
It's normal for a human to poop.
Namanya manusia mau buang hajat.
Help!
Tolong!
It's Fajrul's voice.
Suara Fajrul!
What's wrong with him?
Kenapa dia?
Fajrul!
Fajrul!
Jrul, where are you?
Jrul, di mana, lo?
Stop messing around.
Nyusahin amat ini orang.
Jrul!
Jrul!
Fajrul!
Fajrul!
Something just moved.
Kayak ada yang gerak.
Is that him?
Itu bukan?
Jrul!
Jrul!
Fajrul!
Fajrul!
No, that's a tree.
Bukan, itu pohon!
How can a tree move?
Masa pohon goyang-goyang?
- Fajrul! - Maybe it's the wind.
- Jrul! - Angin, kali.
Goodness!
Astagfirullah.
What happened to you?
Kenapa lo?
- He's allergic to something. - It's your fault for not sharing.
Alergi, nih! Salah makan pasti!
You ate crabs, didn't you?
Wah, makan kepiting ya, lo? Enak banget!
No, it must be shrimps!
Enggak. Udang pasti. Udang, ya?
Shrimps grilled with honey is great…
Wah, kalau udang, dibakar pakai madu tuh, Bang Supra.
Clams! That's it!
Kerang? Kerang!
- What is it? - What?
- Kenapa sih? - Apa sih?
I don't understand. Say it again.
Enggak ngerti gue. Ulang pelan-pelan.
Medan?
Medan?
No!
Bukan!
Sticky rice!
Ketan!
Medan sticky rice with durian!
Ketan Medan pakai durian!
- That's nice! - With coffee…
Itu juga mantap.
Why do you keep kicking me?
Bukan gue yang ngomong! Gue yang ditendang!
What is it?
Kenapa sih? Ditendang?
Is it Tarzan?
Jangan-jangan Tarzan.
Sari.
Sari.
Ghost?
Setan?
Sari is a ghost?
Sari setan?
Don't talk nonsense.
Ngaco, lo! Jangan asal nuduh, lo!
I've already checked her crotch, she's not a ghost!
Gue udah liat lewat selangkangannya, dia bukan setan, kok.
Come again?
Gimana?
You told me to check her crotch.
Gue liat dari selangkangannya. Kan lo suruh!
Show me how you did it.
Coba, gimana? Contohin. Lo liatnya gimana?
- Pretend that you're Sari. - I'm Sari.
- Misalnya ini Sari. - Gue Sari.
Yes.
Iya.
I did this.
Ya udah, gue begini doang.
You're a pervert!
Emang lo mesum!
You should check from your crotch, not hers.
Maksud gue lewat selangkangan lo!
Like this.
Gini, nih.
The food's ready. Come, let's eat.
Makanan udah siap. Ayo kita makan.
What happened to your face?
Kang Fajrul kenapa mukanya?
I think wasps did this.
Ini pasti disengat tawon.
Yes.
Iya.
It's okay, we'll treat you.
Enggak apa. Nanti diobatin.
My wife has finished cooking, let's eat.
Ini kan istri saya udah masak.
Mur, I think we'll just be going home.
Mur, kayaknya kita langsung pulang ke rumah, deh.
What's the rush?
Kenapa jadi buru-buru pulang?
The food is ready. Come on, Sari would be sad.
Makanannya udah jadi. Kasihan istri saya udah masak.
- We're going to… - Do yoga.
- Kita… Kita mau… - Mau yoga!
Yes, right!
- Ah! - Betul.
We're going to do yoga. We want to seek inner peace.
Kita mau yoga. Kita mau cari ketenangan batin dan juga pikiran.
- To control Jaka's temper. - Yes.
- Supaya si Jaka enggak marah-marah mulu. - Iya.
- Anyway, we'll be going now. - Okay.
- Ya udah, Mur, kita pulang duluan. - Ya udah.
I'll bring you the medicine.
Nanti saya anterin obatnya.
Sari S… What did the rest say?
Sari S… S apa ini, kang?
Sari is Sari!
Sari S-A-R-I.
Sari. S-A-R-I.
Sari. S-A-R-I.
That's right!
Oh, iya. Sari S-A-R-I. Iya betul.
Yeah.
Ya.
we should leave this village.
kayaknya mending kita pergi dari kampung ini, deh.
I've had a bad feeling since yesterday.
Itu dia. Dari kemarin, perasaan gue itu udah enggak enak.
But, how can we leave Makmur alone?
Tapi masa kita ninggalin Makmur sendirian?
I know she's his wife.
Itu mah gue udah tahu kalau si Sari istrinya Makmur.
Someone needs to tell him that Sari is a ghost.
Harus ada yang ngasih tahu Makmur kalau si Sari itu setan.
Do you have the heart to leave Makmur?
Memangnya kita tega mau ninggalin si Makmur?
Makmur helped us once.
Makmur itu pernah nolong kita, lho.
And we were in the same squad.
Dan kita pernah satu pasukan bareng dia.
We're like brothers to him.
Kita udah kayak saudara sama si Makmur.
I know that, but we're soldiers.
Saudara sih, saudara, Bang. Tapi kita ini kan tentara.
We were trained to fight humans, not ghosts!
Dilatihnya lawan manusia, bukan lawan setan.
Wait!
Tunggu!
Good thing you haven't left.
Untung belum pada pergi.
- I want to… - Makmur, we've got to tell you something.
- Saya mau… - Makmur,
Don't be vengeful as well.
Jangan dendam juga, ya.
What exactly is going on?
Ini sebenarnya ada apa sih?
Actually…
Sebenarnya…
Solah is going to tell you.
Sebenernya Solah mau ngomong.
Why me?
Kok jadi gue?
Mur.
Mur.
We've been friends for a long time. I've gathered some evidence.
Kita kan temenan udah lama.
The truth is…
yang ternyata… sebenarnya…
Supra is going to tell you!
Bang Supra yang mau ngomong.
Why is it so hard to say it?
Susah banget ngomongnya.
Mur.
Mur.
What did he say?
Apa, ya?
There, there.
Udah, udah.
I know it's hard for you to talk.
Iya. Susah, kan, ngomongnya?
Mur. I'm sorry, but, Sari is…
Mur.
- Pretty! - Yes, she is.
- Cantik, Mur! - Iya, cantik!
- She's always been pretty.
- Cantik. - Itu mah udah dari dulu.
I told you, she always won beauty pageants.
Makanya dari awal saya bilang,
I thought you were going to say something weird!
Saya jadi kaget. Saya kira apa.
I was going to give you this oil.
Ada-ada aja. Ini, saya mau kasih ini.
Use this on your wounds, okay?
Biar cepat sembuh luka disengat tawonnya, ya.
Come on, let's eat.
Ayo makan.
The food is ready.
Masakannya udah jadi.
Didn't you want to try my cooking?
Katanya mau cobain masakan saya?
She'll be disappointed if you don't try it.
Kasian kalau enggak dimakan.
She will be vengeful if you don't.
Nanti Sari bisa dendam, lho.
See, I was right. Your face is a lot better now.
Tuh, kan, bener? Mukanya udah mendingan sekarang.
Makmur. I think Sari is…
Makmur.
But, you still can't speak clearly.
Tapi ngomongnya masih belum jelas.
Slow down.
Pelan-pelan, Kang.
Sari?
Sari?
Sari has…
Sudah. Sari sudah…
- Sari has… - Cooked.
- Sari sudah ma… - Masak!
Sari has cooked.
Oh, Sari sudah masak.
I already told you, she was going to cook today.
Ya, memang tadi sudah saya jelaskan Sari akan masak hari ini.
Please enjoy.
Silakan, Kang.
This looks…
Ini kelihatannya…
like it's high in cholesterol.
mengandung kolesterol, ya.
I have a weak heart.
Saya kebetulan jantungan.
I can't eat high-cholesterol foods.
Enggak bisa sama yang kolesterol.
I also have diabetes.
Saya juga diabetes.
So, I can't eat high-sugar foods.
Jadi, enggak bisa makan makanan yang gula gini.
I have cholesterol, diabetes, high blood pressure.
Saya kolesterol juga, diabetes, darah tinggi.
Come on, don't be shy.
Udah, enggak usah malu-malu.
I know all of you are hungry.
Saya tahu kalian semua pada lapar.
Just try it first, I'm sure you'll like it.
Dicobain aja dulu. Sekali dicoba, pasti langsung ketagihan.
It's your loss if you don't try it. Just one bite.
Rugi kalau enggak coba.
I will be happy if you at least have one bite.
Sesuap aja, saya udah senang.
That means you appreciate what I prepared for Makmur's good friends.
Artinya kalian menghargai apa yang saya sediakan
Supra.
- Kang Supra. - Ya?
How do you like it?
Boleh kasih testimoni.
Delicious.
Enak.
It's delicious. Scrumptious.
Enak. Lezat.
Thank you.
Makasih, Kang.
Jaka, come on, have some.
Kang Jaka, ayo.
Please give us your review.
Silakan ulasannya.
It's yummy!
Enak!
It's amazing!
Mantap! Dahsyat!
Honey, Jaka is a peculiar man.
Neng, Kang Jaka ini orangnya unik.
If he likes something, he will be on fire!
Kalau dia suka sama sesuatu, emosinya meledak-ledak.
That means he's being honest.
Itu tandanya dia jujur.
It's your turn, Solah Vincenzio.
Sekarang Kang Solah Vicenzio.
Please give us a detailed testimony.
Boleh, Kang, testimoninya agak panjangan sedikit, lebih detail.
The texture is delicate.
Teksturnya lembut.
It's full of flavor. Salty, sweet, spicy.
Ini pas masuk di mulut, rasa asin, pedas, manisnya,
It melts on my tongue!
semua luber dalam lidah!
Fajrul.
Kang Fajrul.
I'm sorry,
Ini maaf.
I know it's hard for you to speak, but, as a closing statement,
Walaupun Kang Fajrul masih susah ngomong, tapi sebagai penutup,
please give us your conclusion.
silakan kasih kesimpulannya.
- He said he loves it. - He wants to have more.
- Katanya doyan banget. - Dia pengen nambah.
Give him more.
Kasih.
See?
Tuh, kan?
He loves it so much that he's crying.
Saking sukanya, dia sampai nangis terharu.
As our gratitude,
Sebagai ungkapan terima kasih dari kami,
we prepared desserts.
masih ada camilan penutup.
I will also make you some coffee.
Sekalian saya bikinin kopi, ya?
Wait here, I'll get it.
Sebentar, ambil dulu di belakang.
- Mur. - It's fine.
Mur!
Makmur.
Makmur!
I have to go, I have to finish my laundry.
Saya pamit dulu, ya. Belum ngangkat jemuran.
After that, I have to iron the clothes.
Habis jemuran diangkat kan harus disetrika,
After that, I have to fold the clothes and put them in the drawer.
Habis disetrika mesti dilipat, disusun di lemari. Saya mau nyusun.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
- Hurry up, Jrul! - Have mercy, Sari.
- Buruan, Jrul! - Ampun, Sari!
She's behind you!
Buruan mendekat!
Hurry!
Buruan!
Sari!
Sari!
Why are we not moving forward?
Kenapa kita enggak maju-maju sih?
Hurry up!
Cepet, dong!
Why are we going in circles?
Kenapa jadi muter terus ini?
We meet again!
Ketemu lagi!
You must stop trying to ruin my happiness with Makmur!
Kalian harus berhenti mengganggu kebahagiaan saya dan Kang Makmur!
Promise me!
Janji?
We promise!
Janji!
Pwomish!
Ha-hi.
What?
Apa?
I told you.
Gue bilang juga apa.
Here come the desserts!
Camilan datang!
I got the durian.
Ini udah Akang bawain duren.
They said they wanted some coffee.
Tadi katanya juga pada mau ngopi.
They just left.
Pada pulang, Kang.
They're scared.
Ketakutan.
Scared of what?
Ketakutan kenapa?
They believe what the villagers said, that I'm a ghost.
Mereka percaya omongan orang-orang kampung
Because of Fajrul, we had to speak like that.
Karena Fajrul, kita ngomong harus ikutan cadel.
I also don't want it. Do you think I enjoy it?
Aku juga enggak mau ngomong kayak gini. Kau kira enak?
I can speak.
Bisa ngomong.
You're healed!
Sembuh!
Pwaise bee to Gud!
Alhamdulillah.
- I'm kidding. - Let's go home.
- Bercanda. - Ayo, buruan pulang.
By the way, how about Makmur?
Eh, tapi si Makmur gimana?
What do you mean?
Gimana apaan lagi?
He doesn't know his wife is a ghost.
Kasihan dia. Dia enggak tahu istrinya setan.
Let's just go home.
Udah, yuk. Kita pulang aja.
Who's that?
Siapa itu?
What if it's Sari?
Jangan-jangan Sari.
Don't push me.
Jangan dorong-dorong!
There's no one?
Enggak ada?
No one.
Enggak ada.
- There's no one. - Close it!
- Enggak ada! - Tutup!
You're all traitors.
Kalian semua pengkhianat!
I thought you were my friends.
Saya pikir kalian teman saya.
You're no different to those villagers calling my wife a ghost!
Ternyata sama kayak orang kampung yang nuduh istri saya setan.
Sari is dead, Mur.
Sari itu udah mati, Mur.
The villagers are suspicious of us.
Makanya orang kampung curiga.
So, you trust them more than you trust me?
Kalian lebih percaya mereka dibanding saya, teman kalian?
- This isn't about trust… - They fooled you!
- Ini bukan perkara percaya, Mur. Kita… - Kalian ditipu sama mereka!
You're the one being fooled. You're blinded by love.
Elo yang ditipu, Makmur! Elo udah dibutain sama cinta!
- Your wife and son are ghosts! - You're the ghost!
Anak istri lo itu setan!
We're only like this because we care about you, Makmur.
Kita begini justru karena peduli sama kamu, Makmur!
Makmur, we're brothers.
Makmur, kita ini saudara.
Brothers for life and death forever.
Selamanya saudara, sehidup semati.
Like that?
Gitu?
Brothers.
Saudara.
You can't even be my friends.
Jadi teman aja kalian enggak bisa.
You all came here to ruin my happiness.
Kalian sengaja datang untuk ngancurin kebahagiaan keluarga saya, kan?
I don't need friends like you.
Saya enggak butuh teman kayak kalian.
Leave.
Pergi kalian dari sini.
- Mur! - Makmur!
- Mur! - Makmur!
Let him be.
Udah, biarin aja.
He's blinded by love.
Dibutain cinta dia.
So, we're just leaving him?
Jadi, kita biarin aja dia?
No.
Enggak.
We're brothers.
Benar. Kita ini saudara.
I have another plan.
Aku punya rencana lain.
What is it?
Apa, Bang, rencananya?
I don't have one.
Belum ketemu sih.
Jak, make a plan.
Kamu aja, Jak. Rencananya apa?
How about this…
Ya udah, gini aja.
What? We'll see her?
Ketemu dia?
They crossed the line thinking you're a ghost.
Mereka semua kelewatan kalau masih nyangka Eneng setan.
You were so kind to them. You made them food, you let them stay.
Padahal kamu baik ke mereka.
I can't believe they changed.
Enggak nyangka mereka semua berubah.
Even though they have left,
Mereka pergi pun
the villagers will still talk behind our backs.
orang-orang kampung akan tetap ngomongin kita, Kang.
Don't worry about it.
Enggak usah dipikirin, Neng.
I believe you.
Masih ada Akang yang selalu percaya sama Eneng.
Who cares about what they say?
Masa bodoh orang kampung mau ngomong apa.
What matters is us.
Yang penting kita.
Let's go to the night market.
Kalau perlu, sekarang kita ke pasar malam.
We'll show them that nothing changes.
Kita kasih lihat ke orang-orang kampung, kalau enggak ada yang berubah.
Makmur and Sari are still the same couple.
Makmur dan Sari adalah pasangan suami istri yang masih sama seperti dulu.
What do you think?
Gimana?
What about Cipluk?
Cipluk gimana?
It's okay. We'll come home before he wakes up.
Udah, aman. Nanti kita pulang sebelum dia bangun.
Come on, let's change.
- Ayo. Ganti baju dulu, Neng. - Ayo.
Look at that, honey.
Lihat, Neng!
- Everything looks so fun. - Wait for me!
- Aduh, ini mah seru semua, Neng! - Tunggu!
Let's ride this first!
Kita naik yang ini dulu pertama, Neng!
My balloon.
Balonku…
It's okay, we'll buy you a new one.
Udah, enggak apa-apa. Nanti kita beliin lagi yang baru.
Don't be sad.
Udah, enggak usah sedih, ya?
Here's your balloon.
Ini balonnya.
Thank you.
Makasih.
You're so swift.
Kamu siaga sekali, Sari.
You'll get kidnapped… by a ghost! Come on.
Nanti kamu diculik! Diculik sama setan. Ayo!
That woman. How can there be ghosts at the night market?
Si Ibu. Mana ada setan di pasar malam?
Honey.
Neng.
- Are you still going to wear that mask? - Why?
Topengnya masih mau dipake terus?
Nothing. You're still beautiful.
Enggak apa-apa.
Come.
Yuk.
Once again!
Ya! Sekali lagi, Kang!
It's hard!
Aduh, ini mah susah, Neng.
It's okay, honey.
Enggak apa-apa, Kang.
Sir, stop the ride!
Mas! Berhenti dulu!
Do you want to stop?
Mau berhenti?
Honey!
Akang mah.
Watch, I'll hit all of them.
Lihat, Neng. Jatuh semua sama Akang.
It's okay, honey.
Enggak apa-apa, Kang.
Fireworks!
Kembang api!
So beautiful!
Bagus banget, Neng!
Honey!
Wah, Neng!
I did it!
Akang berhasil, Neng!
I got a doll! It's so cute! Thank you, sir!
Dapat boneka lucu banget. Makasih, Kang.
See, there's too many people here.
Kan, rame ngantrinya.
We might not be able to ride it.
Kalau gini mah, kita bisa enggak kebagian.
Let's ride something else before it gets too late.
Naik yang lain dulu aja. Biar enggak kemaleman.
Fireworks!
Kembang api, Kang!
Where, honey?
Di mana kembang apinya, Neng?
There aren't any.
Enggak ada.
We're being lied to.
Ini mah kita dibohongin!
Honey, it's not crowded anymore.
Neng, udah sepi.
Let's go.
Ayo, Neng.
- Just like old times, right? - Yes.
- Jadi ingat kayak dulu, ya, Neng. - Iya.
Honey.
Neng.
You know that I love you, right?
Neng tahu, kan, Akang cinta sama Eneng?
Yes, honey.
Iya, Kang.
Do you still love me?
Eneng masih cinta enggak, sama Akang?
Why would you ask that?
Akang ngapain nanya?
You know how I feel about you.
Akang kan tahu gimana perasaan Eneng ke Akang.
How do you feel about me?
Ya, perasaannya gimana, Neng?
I love you so much.
Eneng cinta sama Akang.
How much?
Sebesar apa cintanya?
Very, very much.
Banget, banget, Kang.
I love you too.
Akang juga cinta sama Eneng.
Even more than that.
Lebih dari itu, Neng.
Very, very, very much.
Banget, banget, banget.
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak.
We…
Kita kan…
made a promise
pernah janji
not to keep secrets between us.
untuk enggak ada rahasia di antara kita.
That's right.
Iya, betul.
The truth is…
Sebenarnya…
there's something I want to tell you.
ada yang Eneng mau omongin ke Akang.
What? Just tell me.
Ngomongin apa? Ya ngomong atuh, Neng.
But can you promise me?
Tapi Akang janji?
Promise you what?
Janji apa?
Promise me…
Janji…
that if I die first,
kalau Eneng mati duluan,
you'll carry on with your life.
Akang harus terus ngelanjutin hidup Akang.
You can fall in love with another woman.
Akang boleh jatuh cinta sama perempuan lain.
You can marry another woman.
Akang boleh nikah sama perempuan lain.
No.
Enggak.
I can't promise you that.
Akang enggak mau janji.
- Why not? - What are you talking about?
Kenapa sih, Kang?
You know I can't live without you.
Eneng kan tahu Akang enggak bisa hidup tanpa Eneng.
We promised to be together in life and in death.
Lagian kita udah pernah janji kita akan sehidup semati.
With Makmur comes Sari.
Ada Makmur, pasti ada Sari.
Where there's Sari, there's Makmur.
Ada Sari, pasti ada Makmur.
You can't die first.
Eneng enggak boleh mati duluan.
Listen, Kang.
Tapi, Kang!
Fireworks.
Kembang api.
Where?
Di mana kembang apinya?
In your eyes.
Kembang apinya di mata Eneng.
Stop it.
Udah, ya.
Let's stop talking about death.
Berhenti ngomongin mati.
Let's focus on the present. We're alive.
Kenyataannya apa? Kita masih hidup sekarang.
We can still go on ferris wheels together.
Masih bisa naik kincir angin sama-sama.
Why don't we enjoy the moment
Lebih baik sekarang kita nikmatin saat ini.
so we can have wonderful memories?
Biar kita punya kenangan indah.
Memories that will last forever.
Yang enggak akan kita lupain selamanya, Neng.
Finally.
Akhirnya.
You all made it here.
Datang juga ke sini, akhirnya!
Mbak Yu Supi, you're amazing.
Mbah Yu Supi hebat juga, ya.
So you're of royal descent.
Keturunan raja-raja.
This… Kang Mas Pusi. Who is he?
Ini… Kang Mas Pusi.
He's my twin brother.
Saudara kembar saya.
He's also a shaman.
Dukun juga, dia.
You're here because you have a request, right?
Kalian ke sini mau minta, kan? Ya?
You seek my help, yes?
Minta bantuan sama saya?
Yes.
Iya.
To get rid of a ghost?
Ngusir setan, kan?
What's with her?
Apa sih?
Inside that pouch is black sticky rice.
Dalam bungkusan itu, ada ketan hitam.
Grab it.
Ambil.
- Ka. - Jak.
- Ka. - Jak.
You do it, Ka.
Lo aja, Ka.
Black sticky rice.
Ketan hitam.
Excuse me, Mbah Yu.
Permisi, Mbah Yu.
Not that! That's a lizard rice cake!
Bukan yang itu! Itu ketuban kadal!
Lizard rice cake?
Ketuban kadal?
That one.
Ya, itu.
When you pass by the ghost,
Nanti kalau ketemu setannya di jalan,
throw it!
lempar!
It will hurt the ghost.
Nanti mereka kesakitan.
Yes. Thank you, Mbah Yu.
Kalau begitu, terima kasih, Mbah Yu.
Hey.
Hei!
Wait a moment.
Tunggu dulu.
Nothing comes for free in this world.
Tidak ada yang gratis di dunia ini. Tidak ada.
Wouldn't you agree?
Iya, kan? Betul tidak?
We don't have any money, Mbah Yu.
Kita enggak punya duit, Mbah Yu.
Not everything has to be paid with money.
Tidak semua harus dibayar dengan uang.
So…
Jadi…
How should we pay you?
Pakai apa, Mbah Yu?
With a kiss.
Pakai cium.
With you.
Sama kamu.
Yes, you. A kiss with you.
Iya, kamu. Sama kamu.
Was it good?
Enak, Bang?
There. Now you may go.
Udah. Kalian udah boleh pergi sekarang.
Thank you, Mbah Yu.
Permisi, Mbah Yu.
Come on.
Ayo.
Are you sure you want to go in?
Akang yakin mau masuk?
You're scared of ghosts.
Akang kan takut sama setan.
That was before I went to war.
Itu mah dulu, sebelum Akang berangkat perang.
But things have changed.
Sekarang mah beda.
Soldiers aren't afraid of ghosts.
Masa tentara takut sama setan?
No way.
Enggak mungkin.
- Come on. - Okay.
- Ayo, Neng. - Ayo.
Calm down, Sari!
Tenang, Neng!
Don't panic!
Jangan panik!
Don't panic, honey.
Jangan panik, Neng.
You startled me!
Ngagetin aja!
The organizers are insane! It shouldn't be this scary!
Gelo ini panitianya! Enggak gini juga kali mainnya!
My poor wife has a weak heart!
Kasihan istri saya sampai jantungan!
You're mad!
Gelo!
Are you okay?
Eneng aman?
Yes.
Aman.
I know if we go near this pocong,
Akang tahu ini pocong, pasti kalau kita deketin,
it will jump at us.
dia akan ngagetin kita!
It's a pillow.
Bantal ini mah!
Why did he run away?
Kenapa lari?
He even tumbled and crashed…
Sampai akrobat gitu, nabrak…
into the wall.
segala.
He must've been startled because of my shouting.
Pasti takut karena teriakan Akang tadi.
Don't be afraid, Sari.
Jangan takut, Neng.
Where did he go?
Kabur ke mana?
He's afraid of me.
Takut sama Akang.
- Stop crying. - She's scared.
- Jangan nangis! - Takut.
You're bothering us.
Ganggu aja.
What's that now?
Itu apa, Neng?
She's scared. What a dumbass.
Dia takut, goblog.
What's this doing in a haunted house?
Ini ngapain bikin bak di rumah setan?
Trying to scare me? It's not working.
Nakut-nakutin aja. Enggak ada apa-apanya ini mah.
Why'd they keep the little one for the end?
Kenapa yang kecil disisain sih, Neng?
Come on, you can do it.
Ayo, bisa! Ayo, naik!
You can do it, come on.
Ayo, bisa!
All good.
Aman.
- Are you okay? - Yeah.
- Neng aman? - Aman.
The last one.
Ini yang terakhir.
A forest setup.
Kawasan hutan pasti.
There's no reason to be scared.
Kalau ini kita enggak usah takut.
We live in a forest.
Namanya juga kita hidup di hutan.
It'll just be snakes at worst.
Paling juga ular.
I'll go check and make sure it's safe for you.
Akang cek dulu biar Eneng enggak takut.
Let's go!
Ayo!
Kang?
Kang?
Kang Mak?
Kang Mak?
Kang!
Kang!
Don't hurt me.
Jangan bunuh saya!
Knock him out so we can carry him easily.
Pingsanin aja, biar gampang bawanya.
You guys again?
Kalian lagi.
Why did you follow me here?
Ngapain sih, kalian ikutin saya ke sini?
What are you doing now?
Ini lagi, mau ngapain sih?
Stop!
Udah!
Leave me and Sari alone.
Pokoknya jangan gangguin saya sama Sari!
Go back to your own villages.
Udah, pulang aja ke kampung kalian!
You're getting on my nerves.
Ganggu aja kalian semua.
- Hurry up. - Tie him up.
- Buruan! - Cepat!
Hey. The door is locked.
Bang, pintunya dikunci.
Are you sure?
Hah? Masa sih?
Seriously? Let me try.
Yang bener, lo? Coba!
Crap! What do we do?
Ya elah! Gimana ini, Bang?
We have to resort to using strategy 21.
Kita terpaksa menggunakan strategi 21.
Shed the insect's skin.
Lepaskan kulit serangga.
Isn't it dangerous? It's a haunted house.
Apa enggak bahaya, Bang? Ini kan rumah setan.
There's no other way.
Enggak ada jalan lain.
Mommy.
Mama…
Who are you?
Siapa kamu?
I'm…
Saya…
Suprawati.
Suprawati.
Hadiningrum.
Hadiningrum.
There's absolutely no way I'm trying this strategy again.
Pokoknya saya enggak mau lagi pakai strategi lepaskan kulit serangga.
And you call yourself a soldier?
Tentara gitu aja takut!
Use your normal voice.
Suaranya biasa aja.
Hey, where's Fajrul?
Hei! Fajrul mana?
Right.
Oh, iya.
Where's she? Is she gone?
Di mana dia? Udah pergi, kan, Bang?
Sorry.
Maaf, Lah.
Now we have to get Makmur.
Sekarang, kita harus ambil Makmur.
- Over there? - Yeah.
- Ke sana, Bang? - Ke sana!
Come on.
Ayo!
Have mercy, Sari.
Ampun, Sari.
Forgive us.
Ampun.
Sari, who?
Sari, Sari!
I'm Wewe Gombel!
Gue Wewe Gombel!
Why?
Kenapa sih?
I've been here all week,
Udah seminggu gue di sini,
but I couldn't scare anyone.
enggak ada satu pun orang yang takut sama gue.
I beg you!
Minta tolong saya, Mas.
Can you please be afraid or startled?
Takut gitu, kek. Kaget, kek.
I'm scared…
Takut…
So scary.
- Takut. - Seram.
You're faking it.
Pura-pura, ya, Mas?
Please be afraid!
Takut dong, Mas. Tolong!
You're exaggerating, Solah.
Berlebihan, Solah.
- I'm trying to get this over with. - Too dramatic.
Ya, biar selesai aja dia.
I'm going home.
Saya pulang aja.
She's scarier anyway.
Dia lebih seram.
"She"?
Hah? "Dia"?
Give me back my husband or you'll be sorry.
Kembalikan suami saya atau kalian akan menyesal!
The black sticky rice!
Ketan hitam! Ketan hitam!
- It's in the pouch! - The black sticky rice!
- Di tas! - Ketan hitam!
The black sticky rice!
Ketan hitam!
Are we clear?
Udah aman!
Where are you taking me?
Kalian bawa saya ke mana ini?
Sari?
Sari?
Where's Sari?
Sari mana?
Honey!
Neng!
Where is she, guys?
Sari di mana, Kang?
Calm down. We're getting you out of here.
Tenang, Mur. Kita harus bawa lo pergi.
- Are you trying to separate me from Sari? - Sari is a ghost.
Kalian misahin saya sama Sari?
Yesterday, I…
Aku kemarin…
It's Sari.
Sari, Sari.
Honey?
Neng?
- Sari! Help… - Stop!
- Sari! Tolong… - Hei!
Can you quiet down? I'm trying to pee.
Ya elah. Pada berisik banget. Gue pengen kencing nih!
It's a huge forest and you're peeing here?
Lo hutan segede gini, kencing di sini!
It's a huge forest and you're chatting here?
Lo hutan segede gini, malah ngobrol di sini.
You can't tell me what to do. Go away!
Lah? Ngatur-ngatur gue, lo? Pergi, lo!
- Try me! - You try me!
- Sini, lo! - Elo yang sini!
Stop it!
Udah!
I'm going home.
Saya mau pulang pokoknya!
- Hey. - Mur!
- Heh! - Mur!
Mur!
Mur!
We're trying to help you.
Kita itu mau nolong kamu, Makmur!
He's right. You're living with a ghost.
Iya, Mur. Lo itu tinggal sama setan!
Sari is not a ghost.
Sari itu bukan setan, Kang!
You're so stubborn.
Ngeyel banget, ya, ini orang!
Makmur.
Makmur.
I found her skeleton in the bushes.
Aku nemu tengkorak di semak-semak.
How would you know it's her?
Tahu dari mana itu tengkoraknya Sari?
The skeleton had a wedding ring on it.
Tengkoraknya pakai cincin kawin, Makmur!
Some skeletons are dressed in suits.
Tapi ada tengkorak yang dikubur pakai jas.
Some in wedding dresses or traditional outfits.
Ada yang pakai baju pengantin, baju tradisional.
Give it a rest.
Udah lah, Kang.
I know I'm not the smartest,
Saya ini emang enggak pintar,
but don't make a fool of me.
tapi jangan dibego-begoin terus.
I love her.
Saya itu cinta sama Sari.
No matter what happens,
Jadi, apa pun yang terjadi,
I will never leave her.
saya enggak akan ninggalin Sari.
If you're gonna keep doing this,
Kalau terus seperti ini, lebih baik kalian pergi dari hidup saya.
You said we were brothers.
Katanya kalian saudara.
What kind of brothers would split a husband from his wife?
Mana ada saudara yang mau pisahin suami sama istrinya?
You guys are cruel.
Kalian mah jahat.
Makmur!
Makmur!
He hasn't changed at all.
Makmur tabiatnya tidak pernah berubah.
Stubborn as ever.
Masih saja keras kepala.
We have to come up with a plan.
Kita harus cari cara.
Jaka, you're the closest person to him.
Jaka, kau adalah orang yang paling dekat dengan dia.
In the barracks, you're the one he slept with the most.
Selama di barak, dia paling sering tidur bersamamu.
Solah.
Solah.
You're from the village closest to Makmur.
Kau adalah orang yang kampungnya paling dekat dengan Makmur.
And you, Supra.
Dan kau, Supra.
You've been the group's leader for the longest time.
Kau adalah orang yang paling lama memimpin grup ini.
I don't care what it takes,
Aku enggak mau tahu bagaimana caranya,
we must save Makmur.
kita harus menyelamatkan Makmur.
Do you understand?
Mengerti kau?
Supra.
Bang.
Before, during, and after I recovered from the wasp sting,
Aku dari sehat, disengat tawon, sampai sehat lagi,
Makmur is still stubborn.
Makmur enggak bisa dibilangin, Bang.
What do we do?
Gimana ini, Bang?
Listen up! This is no time to be messing around.
Dengar, ya! Ini bukan saatnya lagi kita main-main.
No matter how deep our wounds are,
Sedalam apa pun luka yang kita derita,
nothing can separate us as brothers.
tidak ada yang bisa memisahkan kita semua sebagai saudara.
Remember who we are.
Ingat siapa kita!
We are true soldiers!
Tentara sejati!
Help!
Tolong!
- Makmur!
Makmur!
You're supposed to say,
Seharusnya kan nyautnya,
"Yessir!"
"Siap, dong!"
Makmur! What's the matter?
Makmur, kenapa?
My stomach hurts.
Perut saya sakit, Kang.
Constipation?
Pengen berak kali itu.
What's wrong with him?
Makmur kenapa?
His gunshot wound hasn't healed.
Luka tembaknya belum sembuh, Bang.
Give this to Makmur.
Kasih Makmur.
Mur.
Mur.
- Will that work? - Yes. It's a remedy from when I was a kid.
- Emang bisa, Bang? - Bisa.
- You got shot when you were a kid? - No. It's for scabs.
- Abang kecil-kecil udah kena tembak? - Kagak. Korengan, kudis.
Once applied, it heals within five minutes.
Begitu dioles, lima menit langsung sembuh.
If Makmur thinks Sari is still alive,
Kalau menurut Makmur Sari itu masih hidup,
whose skeleton did Fajrul find?
berarti tengkorak yang ditemukan Fajrul tengkorak siapa?
But Fajrul said the skeleton was wearing the same wedding ring as Sari.
Kata Fajrul, tengkoraknya itu pakai cincin kawin yang sama
That's strange.
Tapi aneh juga, ya.
I thought when someone dies,
Setahu gue, kalau udah mati,
they wouldn't be wearing rings, necklaces, or any jewelry.
enggak akan bawa cincin, kalung, apalagi perhiasan.
Right.
Iya juga, ya.
Kuntilanak don't wear earrings.
Mana ada kuntilanak pakai anting?
If the skeleton had a wedding ring,
Kalau tengkorak itu pakai cincin kawin,
then Makmur should have the same ring as Sari.
seharusnya si Makmur pakai cincin yang sama kayak yang dipakai Sari.
Check his fingers.
Sekarang coba lo cek.
Let me see your right hand for a sec.
Coba lihat tangan kanannya, ya. Sebentar aja.
He doesn't have it.
Enggak ada cincinnya.
That means…
Berarti…
What? You startled me.
Apa sih? Ngagetin aja!
What are you doing?
Kalian ngapain sih?
Sari is not the ghost.
Sari bukan setan.
The ghost is Makmur.
Setannya itu Makmur.
Nonsense.
Jangan sembarangan nuduh!
Makmur is dead.
Makmur itu udah mati.
The skeleton you found is Makmur.
Tengkorak yang lo temuin itu punya Makmur.
- Right. - What?
Betul.
If you believe me… Jak!
Kalau enggak percaya… Jak!
Throw the black sticky rice at him.
Lempar pakai ketan hitam.
A ghost!
Setan!
I can't believe Makmur is the ghost.
Enggak nyangka, si Makmur itu ternyata setan.
We've been with a ghost all this time.
Berarti selama ini kita barengan sama setan.
We also accepted him as our brother.
Mana kita angkat jadi saudara lagi.
So Makmur was already a ghost during the war?
Berarti, selama perang, Makmur jadi setan, ya?
The body I found was already a skeleton.
Soalnya mayat itu udah jadi tengkorak.
Perhaps.
Ya, bisa jadi.
I feel sorry for Sari.
Kasian si Sari.
She's… been accused of being a ghost.
Selama ini… dia dituduh setan.
Sari.
Sari.
That means Sari is innocent.
Berarti Sari itu perempuan benar.
And I will protect her
Dan gue akan ngelindungi dia.
until death do us part.
Sampai ajal menjemput.
What the heck?
Apaan sih?
Are you serious?
Lo serius, Sol?
Are you seriously thinking about
Dalam kondisi kayak gini pun, lo masih mikirin gantiin posisi Makmur?
It's about humanity.
Ini soal kemanusiaan.
Humanity, my foot!
Kemanusiaan?
Sari is a beautiful woman.
Sari itu wanita cantik.
We can't leave her alone.
Kasihan kalau dia ditinggal sendiri di sini.
She needs a man willing to take on the responsibility
Harus ada lelaki yang berani ambil tanggung jawab
of protecting her.
untuk ngelindungin dia.
And that would be…
Dan itu adalah…
Solah Vicenzio.
Solah Vicenzio.
Sari.
Sari.
I'm coming for you.
Abang datang, Sari.
Sari!
Sari!
Solah, wait.
Tunggu dulu.
You sure she's not the ghost?
Kau yakin Sari bukan setan?
She served us worms and insects the other day.
Soalnya yang kita makan kemarin itu cacing, serangga gitu.
I'm sure.
Yakin.
I'm sure she's not a ghost.
Gue yakin Sari bukan setan.
You just don't know.
Main lo aja kurang jauh.
That kind of food is common in Thailand.
Di Thailand, makanan kayak gitu biasa aja.
Worms are a source of protein.
Cacing tuh mengandung protein.
Besides, Sari's father is from Thailand.
Lagian, bapak si Sari orang Thailand.
Really?
Emang iya?
I'm not sure. But he could be.
Enggak tahu sih. Iya kali.
Maybe.
Iya sih.
Come on.
Ya udah.
Sari. I've come here with my friends
Sari, kedatangan saya ke sini bersama teman-teman
to apologize because we accused you
ingin meminta maaf, karena…
of being a ghost.
kami telah menuduh kamu setan.
But it appears we were mistaken. You're simply a charming woman.
Ternyata kamu bukan setan. Kamu hanyalah
We must leave, Sari.
Sekarang kita harus segera pergi, Sari.
- Where? - To a new place.
Ke mana?
Start a new life
Menempuh hidup yang baru
with a new partner.
bersama pasangan yang baru.
Where's Kang Makmur?
Kang Makmur di mana?
Makmur is waiting upstream.
Makmur sudah menunggu di hulu.
As for us… we're going to the officiant.
Dan, kita berdua, ke penghulu.
What he's saying is…
Eh, maksudnya…
Let's go upstream because Makmur is waiting there.
Kita ke hulu sungai karena Makmur udah di sana.
- Really? - Yes.
- Beneran? - Benar.
You should get ready
Sekarang kamu siap-siap dan bawa anak kita pergi.
I mean, your child.
Anak kamu, maksudnya.
Cipluk.
Cipluk.
Where's Makmur?
Kang Makmur di mana?
He's just up ahead. Right, guys?
Ada di depan. Iya, kan, Teman-Teman?
- Yeah. - Up ahead.
- Iya. - Iya, di depan.
The boat's leaking.
Perahunya masuk air ini!
Here, the bags! Toss out all the bags.
Tas! Buang tas!
There's more.
Satu lagi tuh.
- What about now? - It's still leaking.
- Gimana? - Masih!
Drop everything we're holding.
Ini! Yang kita pegang, buang!
That's all of it!
Udah enggak ada lagi!
Good.
Aman.
"Good" my foot!
"Aman" apaan!
How can we move? You tossed the paddle.
Kita jalannya gimana, dayung dibuang?
Jaka!
Jaka!
Jrul, you go.
Aduh.
No. I can't swim.
Enggak. Aku enggak bisa berenang.
There's Makmur!
Itu Kang Makmur!
- Where are you taking my wife and kid? - We're getting them out of here.
Mau dibawa ke mana anak dan istri saya?
You're the ghost!
Kau setannya!
How could he be the ghost?
Gimana Kang Makmur setannya?
Makmur died in the war.
Makmur udah mati di medan perang.
But he didn't realize it. None of us did.
Tapi dia enggak sadar. Kita semua juga enggak ada yang sadar.
His body was already sent back here
Padahal mayatnya udah dikirim pulang.
and secretly buried behind your house, Sari.
Diam-diam, dikubur di belakang rumah kamu, Sari.
But don't worry, Sari.
Tapi kamu tenang aja, Sari.
I will protect you.
Ada aku yang melindungi kamu.
Give me back my family!
Kembalikan keluarga saya!
Mur! Don't come here!
Enggak usah ke sini, Mur!
- Mur, stop! - Use your hands!
Mur, jangan!
Kang Makmur!
Kang Makmur!
Kang!
- Kang! - Ampun!
- Kang Makmur! - Mur!
- Kang Makmur! - Mur!
Help!
Tolong!
- My legs are cramping! - Come on up.
- Kaki saya keram. Tolong. - Ayo.
Why did you run away from me?
Lagian kenapa kalian lari dari saya sih tadi?
We all thought you were the ghost.
Tadi kita semua mikir lo tuh setan.
None of us thought that.
Enggak ada yang mikir begitu.
But Jaka did.
Cuma si Jaka doang, Mur, yang mikir begitu.
He screamed when I threw the sticky rice at him.
Enggak! Tadi kan waktu saya lempar ketan, dia teriak.
The sticky rice went into my wound, it really hurt.
Ketannya masuk ke dalem luka saya, Kang. Sakit banget itu.
What about your wedding ring?
Terus cincin kawin lo mana, Mur?
- Here's my ring. - He has it.
- Ini cincin saya. - Ada.
I made it into a necklace before I left for war.
Emang saya jadiin kalung sebelum perang.
Can we stop talking about ghosts? Focus on the boat.
Bisa berhenti enggak ngomongin setan? Fokus ke perahu.
The boat's almost full of water.
Ini air masuk semua!
Come on, paddle with your hands.
Ya udah, ayo. Dayung pakai tangan.
Careful.
Jangan goyang-goyang.
- Hold on! - What?
Tunggu.
First we assumed Sari was the ghost, then it turned out to be Makmur.
Tadi waktu kita pikir Sari yang setan, ternyata Makmur yang setan.
Now that Makmur is not the ghost, who's the real ghost?
Tapi sekarang Makmur bukan setan. Berarti yang setan siapa?
We'll turn into ghosts if this boat sinks.
Yang ada kita yang jadi setan kalau ini tenggelam.
Makmur's here too.
Mana ditambah si makmur.
It's getting heavier.
Perahunya kan makin berat.
Let's get the boat to shore first.
Udah, yang penting sekarang ke pinggir dulu.
How? Using our hands to paddle isn't working.
Mau ke pinggir pakai apa? Tadi kan kayuh pakai tangan enggak jalan.
Use this.
Pakai ini.
Thanks, Sari.
Makasih, Sari.
What now, Jak?
Kenapa lagi sih, Jak?
What are you waiting for?
Nunggu apa lagi, Jaka?
Supra! Move aside.
Bang Supra! Minggir, Bang Supra!
Where?
Minggir ke mana?
Doesn't matter.
Ke kanan, ke kiri, terserah.
Yup, like that.
Ya, minggir. Nah.
- You next, Mur. - What you doing?
- Makmur! - Mau ngapain?
Just listen to me this once.
Ya udah, yang ini nurut sama gue dulu, ya.
Fajrul, you go left.
Fajrul, lo minggir juga!
Fajrul, you move aside too.
Fajrul juga minggir.
Supra! Who told you to sit straight?
Aduh, Bang Supra kenapa bangun lagi sih?
My back hurts, Jaka.
Pinggang encok, Jaka!
Just bear with it for a sec.
Iya, tahan dulu sebentar!
Solah, you move!
Nah. Solah minggir!
- Where? - Anywhere!
Gue ke mana?
- Just do it, Solah. - Just lean sideways.
- Dikasih tahu minggir, minggir aja. - Minggir aja!
Don't make this harder.
Susah kali dikasih tahu.
Supra lean left, Makmur lean right.
Bang Supra kiri, Makmur kanan.
- Okay. - I'm going left.
- Iya. - Ya, aku kiri.
Hold on. What are we doing?
Enggak, bentar dulu. Ini mau ngapain sih?
Just do it, Solah.
Kau nurut aja. Susah kali!
True soldiers!
Tentara sejati!
Yessir!
Siap, dong!
Good morning, noon, and night We are true soldiers
Selamat pagi, siang, malam
Soldiers of this land Fighting for our country
Pasukan bumi pertiwi
This is our spirit
Ini jiwa kami
Forever brothers, in life and death
Selamanya saudara, Sehidup semati
Sari is the ghost!
Sari setan!
She's the ghost!
Aduh, Sari setan!
I saw it!
Gue udah lihat! Gue udah…
Can't ghosts wear rings?
Emang setan enggak bisa pakai cincin?
She's a ghost!
Sari setan!
Sari?
Sari?
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak.
Jump! All of you!
Lompat!
Let's go, Mur!
Ayo, Mur!
Sari!
Sari!
Wait.
Bentar dulu.
We're missing one.
Kok kita cuma berempat?
Where's Fajrul?
Fajrul mana?
Sari!
Sari!
Fajrul, jump!
Fajrul, loncat!
Rul, hurry up!
Jrul, buruan!
How?
Loncat apa? Aku enggak bisa berenang!
Sari.
Sari.
Let's just have a chat.
Kita ngobrol-ngobrol aja, ya?
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Not gonna answer?
Enggak dijawab gue?
You look pale. Are you anemic?
Kamu pucat. Kurang darah, ya?
You should eat more fruits.
Banyak makan buah, ya.
They increase blood levels.
Biar darahnya nambah.
You don't like fruits?
Enggak mau, ya?
I don't think you want to talk to me.
Kayaknya enggak mau diajak ngobrol, ya?
Help.
Tolong.
I think you're not in the mood to talk.
Kamu enggak minat ngomong, ya?
He's so fast!
Cepat banget.
You said you couldn't swim.
Katanya enggak bisa berenang.
You swam like a champion.
Lo berenang kayak atlet pelatnas.
Honey.
Neng!
We have to go now.
Kita harus pergi, Mur.
No, I can't.
Enggak bisa, Kang.
I promised her,
Saya udah janji sama Sari
I would never leave her.
enggak akan ninggalin dia sampai kapan pun.
What was that for?
Ngapain Akang mukul saya?
It wasn't me. Him.
Bukan aku, kan? Tuh.
Right.
Oh, iya. Bukan.
What was that for?
Tadi Akang yang mukul saya?
Sari…
Neng…
I will never leave you.
Akang enggak akan ninggalin Eneng.
He knocks himself out a lot, huh?
Hobi banget ini orang nyakitin diri sendiri.
Sari's angry!
Sari ngamuk!
Come on! Hurry!
Ayo, buruan!
Where are we going?
Jadi, kita ke mana ini?
Let's go to Mbak Yu Supi's place.
Mau ke rumahnya Mbah Yu Supi.
Let's go.
Ya udah, ayo.
Wait!
Ntar dulu!
Wait. Isn't that Mbak Yu Supi?
Ntar dulu. Itu Mbah Yu Supi?
She's dead. Sari must've killed her.
Dia udah mati.
- Help her out. - Wait.
- Ayo tolongin. - Bentar.
Makmur might wake up soon.
Ini entar Makmur keburu bangun.
What if people think we killed her?
Lagian, nanti kalau kita disalahin gimana?
Where do we go?
Terus kita ke mana?
I know a place.
Aku tahu kita mesti ke mana.
- Come with me. - Okay.
- Ikut aku. - Ayo.
Of course…
Yang jelas…
I will not just stand still
saya tidak akan tinggal diam
after my twin sister was murdered.
untuk membalas kematian saudara kembar saya.
I will help you
Saya akan membantu kalian
fight that ghost.
untuk melawan setan itu.
How, Kang Mas?
Caranya gimana, Kang Mas?
I will try to summon the spirit of my twin
Saya akan mencoba memanggil arwah kembaran saya
to enter my body.
untuk masuk ke dalam tubuh saya ini.
Rames rice…
Nasinya, nasi rames…
There are four ways to defeat this ghost.
Ada empat cara untuk melawan setan ini.
Number one.
Yang pertama,
Prepare black sticky rice.
kita siapkan ketan hitam.
Number two.
Yang kedua,
A garden of flowers.
kembang setaman.
A carton flower?
Tembang kenangan?
Number three.
Dan yang ketiga,
I've imbued this wooden sword with spells
pedang kayu ini sudah saya berikan mantra-mantra
to send that ghost to the afterlife forever.
untuk melawan setan itu ke akhirat selamanya.
Don't let this sword fall into the hands
Jangan sampai pedang ini jatuh ke tangan
of irresponsible people.
orang-orang yang tidak bertanggung jawab.
Yes, Kang Mas.
Ya, Kang Mas.
It could be dangerous.
Bisa berbahaya.
Exploited.
Disalahgunakan.
Give it here!
Sini!
Lastly.
Dan yang keempat.
This rope…
Tali ini,
has been coated with Cemani chicken blood.
sudah saya lumuri darah ayam cemani.
This acts as a guard and a barrier between you.
Ini berfungsi sebagai penjaga dan pembatas antara kalian.
Thus, I call this
Makanya tali ini saya namakan
the bond of kinship.
tali silaturahmi.
Hold on.
Bentar dulu.
You've given tasks to the three of us, but what about Supra?
Kita bertiga udah dapat tugas nih.
Just curious.
Nanya doang.
Don't let the baldie slip away.
Yang botak jangan sampai lolos nih.
Mister Supra.
Bang Supra.
You should stay with me.
Dampingin aku aja.
Go for it.
Sikat, Bang.
Make sure no one steps outside this barrier.
Jangan ada satu pun yang keluar dari tali pembatas ini.
As long as we're inside here, the ghost won't come near.
Setan itu tidak akan bisa mendekati kita kalau kita ada di dalam sini.
You're the best, Kang Mas Pusi.
Emang paling jago, Kang Mas Pusi.
She left.
Dia pergi.
What did you say?
Lo ngomong apa tadi?
I said you're the best.
Ngomong jago doang.
Don't say that.
Jangan ngomong gitu!
Supi is sulking.
Supi ngambek tuh!
We had no idea, Kang Mas.
Kan kita enggak tahu, Kang Mas.
Yeah.
Iya.
Give it another try before Sari shows up.
Mending dicoba lagi aja sebelum si Sari datang.
Okay. I don't think I'm strong enough by myself.
Iya. Soalnya kalau saya sendirian, enggak kuat.
What about us?
Apalagi kita?
Delivery!
Paket!
Delivery?
Paket?
Leave it outside.
Taruh aja di depan!
Let's try again.
Kita coba lagi.
Padang rice…
Nasinya, nasi padang…
What else did you order?
Mesen apa lagi sih, Kang Mas?
Nothing.
Enggak ada.
Don't take a single step back.
Jangan mundur!
- Step forward! - Don't step back.
- Maju! - Jangan mundur.
- You're moving back! - I'm getting my stance ready.
- Mundur. - Saya lagi ambil ancang-ancang.
Stop pushing me.
Jangan ditahan.
Don't step back!
Jangan! Jangan mundur.
You're moving back!
Mundur.
Don't be afraid. Stand up.
Jangan takut! Berdiri!
Arm yourselves.
Siapkan senjata kalian.
Chicken porridge!
Bubur ayam!
- No porridge. - That one.
- Enggak ada. - Itu!
- Sticky black rice. - Yes, that one.
- Ketan hitam! - Iya, itu.
Here.
Ini.
You do it.
Kasih dong!
Not me.
Masa saya?
Did I get her?
Kena enggak?
We did it!
Kita berhasil!
That's amazing.
- Wah! - Jago juga, ya.
- Honey? - Kang Makmur!
- Neng? - Kang Makmur!
Sari?
Sari?
- Kang Makmur. - Sari!
- Kang Makmur. - Sari!
- Makmur, stop!
- Makmur!
Sari!
Sari!
Second weapon! The garden of flowers!
Kembang setaman! Lepas setaman!
- You have it! - Stop!
- Elo, kembang setaman! - Jangan!
Sari! Stop! You're hurting her!
Sari! Berhenti! Jangan sakitin Sari!
Mak! Get a grip!
Mak! Lo sadar!
That's a ghost! An evil spirit!
Dia itu setan! Dia itu jahat!
A demon! Cursed! She belongs in hell! She has no good values!
Dia itu iblis! Dia itu laknat!
- Open your eyes! - Enough.
- Lo sadar! - Udah. Nyelanya banyak banget lo.
You demon! Devil!
Dasar lo iblis! Setan!
You belong in hell! You wretch!
Penghuni neraka! Penjahat kamu!
- Pharaoh's crony. - Pharaoh's crony!
- Kawan firaun. - Kawan firaun!
- Pale skinned. - Pale skinned!
- Pucat! - Pucat kamu ini!
- Banished in hell… - Go say it yourself.
- Siksa neraka… - Ngomong aja sendiri!
No! I'm too scared.
Enggak berani.
I never killed anyone.
Saya tidak pernah membunuh siapa pun.
Liar! We don't believe you!
Bohong! Kami tidak percaya.
As I said, I didn't kill anyone!
Sudah saya bilang, saya tidak membunuh siapa pun!
Sari! Let me go!
Sari!
The sword!
Pedang!
You do it. I'm just here to cast spells.
Ya kamu dong. Saya cuma doa-doa doang.
No! Sari!
Jangan! Sari!
Hurry up!
Tebas, buruan!
Makmur!
Makmur!
Makmur, stop!
Makmur, tidak!
Hold him!
Tahan!
- Sari! - What's next?
- Sari! - Kita mesti ngapain, Kang Mas?
Only one way left.
Tinggal satu cara terakhir.
This is a forbidden technique.
Dan cara ini adalah cara terlarang.
Don't! Sari!
Jangan! Sari!
- Mak, calm down! Makmur! - Sari! Run!
- Mak! Makmur! - Pergi, Sari!
Don't sacrifice yourself.
Jangan ngorbanin diri sendiri!
- Don't hurt Sari! - Kang Mas Pusi!
- Jangan sakitin Sari! - Kang Mas Pusi!
Enough!
Udah!
- Calm down. - Let him handle it as best he can.
- Tenang. - Biar dia selesaikan dengan cara terbaik.
Sari. Listen to me.
Sari, dengarkan saya baik-baik.
Do you have any idea
Kamu tahu enggak,
what the most dangerous occupation in the world is?
profesi yang paling berisiko tinggi di dunia ini tuh apa?
A shaman. Why?
Dukun!
They fight ghosts. Take me, for example.
Musuhnya setan.
I don't want to be hostile towards ghosts
Saya itu enggak mau musuhan sama setan,
or be mean to them.
jahat sama setan.
- What's the point of yelling, threatening? - What is he talking about?
- Ngapain ribut, teriak, mengancam? - Apaan sih?
I just want to have a chat,
Saya mah pengennya baik-baik aja.
What do you say, Sar?
Jadi, gimana nih, Sar?
Could we perhaps
Kira-kira ada kemungkinan, enggak,
have a chat over some delicious coffee?
kita ngobrol-ngobrol sambil ngopi-ngopi cantik, gitu?
I guess that's a no? It's okay.
Enggak, ya? Ya udah enggak apa-apa.
Perhaps you're busy.
Mungkin Sari lagi sibuk.
Excuse me.
Permisi, Sar.
I'm heading out.
Gue cabut dulu, ya.
What about us?
Terus ini gimana, Kang Mas?
This is your domestic affair,
Ini kan masalah internal rumah tangga, beresin aja dulu.
I'm an outsider, it's not my place to intervene.
Saya kan orang luar, enggak pantas saya ikut campur.
Okay?
Ya?
Makmur, no!
Makmur!
Sari, run away!
Pergi, Sari!
Stop!
Hentikan!
My package is outside.
Paket saya ketinggalan di depan.
Excuse me. Just grabbing my package.
Permisi, Sar. Ngambil paket.
Run, Sari! Save yourself!
Sari! Selamatkan diri, Sari!
Why are we tied up?
Kita jadi terikat begini.
Now it's your turn to feel pain.
Sekarang saatnya kalian yang merasa tersiksa.
Sari. Please don't hurt me.
Sari! Jangan, Sari.
You should've stayed out of my life with Kang Makmur.
Seharusnya kalian tidak mengganggu kehidupan saya dengan Kang Makmur.
Sar! Get a grip!
Sar! Sadar!
- You don't belong here! - I don't care!
Lo tuh beda alam!
She doesn't care?
Dia enggak peduli.
I just want to be together again with the person I love.
Saya cuma mau hidup bersama lagi dengan orang yang saya cintai.
That's not love. That's toxic.
Itu bukan cinta! Itu toksik!
Sari.
Sari.
Think about Makmur's life.
Ingat kehidupan Makmur, Sari.
If Makmur stays with you, the villagers will shun him.
Kalau Makmur sama kamu, dijauhin sama warga kampung!
Shut up!
Diam!
You've made me even angrier.
Kalian membuat saya makin marah!
We're sorry, Sari.
Maaf, ya, Sari.
There's no need to be offended. That's just the way they talk.
Maafin, jangan kepancing.
It's too late.
Terlambat.
Now I'll make you go through the pain I felt.
Sekarang kalian harus merasakan sakit yang saya alami tadi.
I will finish you off one by one,
Kalian akan saya habisi satu per satu
until no one remains to interfere with our lives.
sampai tidak ada lagi yang bisa mengganggu kehidupan kami.
No!
Jangan, Sari.
Honey.
Neng…
Honey, stop it.
Neng, udah.
Don't do it.
Udah. Jangan, Neng.
Please, don't do this.
Kasihan teman-teman Akang.
They didn't mean any harm to you.
Mereka semua enggak bermaksud jahat sama Eneng. Enggak.
They just wanted to help me.
Mereka cuma mau nolongin Akang.
Because we promised
Karena kita udah janji
to fight together as brothers in life and in death.
untuk berjuang bersama-sama sebagai saudara sehidup semati.
But as long as they're here,
Tapi, Kang, selama mereka masih ada,
they will interfere with our lives.
mereka akan mengganggu kehidupan kita.
But if you hurt them, especially if you kill them,
Tapi kalau Eneng nyakitin mereka, apalagi sampai membunuh mereka,
then it only proves them right.
berarti benar yang mereka katakan.
You're evil.
Eneng yang jahat.
Honey.
Neng.
To live in the same world…
Biar dunia kita sama…
so that nobody bothers us,
biar enggak ada lagi orang yang ganggu kita berdua…
including them,
termasuk mereka…
it would be better…
lebih baik…
for you to take me.
Eneng yang bunuh Akang.
Do you mean it?
Benar, Akang rela?
Yes.
Rela, Neng.
Makmur!
Makmur!
Sari, no!
Jangan, Sari!
Sari!
Sari!
You know…
Akang tahu…
I couldn't possibly hurt you,
Eneng enggak mungkin nyakitin Akang sedikit pun.
much less kill you.
Apalagi ngebunuh Akang.
You promised me.
Akang udah janji sama Neng
To be together in life and in death.
kalau kita akan sehidup semati.
I've always kept that promise.
Akang selalu pegang janjinya, Neng.
I always remember.
Akang selalu ingat.
That's why I've stayed with you from the start.
Makanya, dari awal Akang bertahan sama Eneng.
Even though I knew that…
Walaupun akan tahu…
You…
Eneng…
You were gone.
Eneng udah enggak ada.
You knew from the start?
Akang udah tahu dari awal?
Did they say anything about me?
Mereka ngomongin tentang Eneng, enggak, Kang?
I'm so sorry.
Maafin Akang, Neng.
I came home too late.
Akang terlambat pulang.
Even if all the villagers shun me,
Walaupun semua orang kampung ngejauhin Akang,
and nobody wants to be my friend.
enggak ada yang mau jadi teman Akang…
Even if they think I'm crazy.
Bahkan mereka mungkin mengira Akang orang gila.
I will stay with you.
Akang tetap bertahan, Neng.
I'm not going anywhere.
Akang enggak pergi sedikit pun.
I will never leave you.
Akang enggak ninggalin Eneng.
And even if I have to
Dan walaupun setiap hari…
eat dried leaves every day
Akang harus makan daun kering…
with centipedes and maggots,
dengan lauk kelabang dan belatung,
I'm really happy.
tapi Akang senang.
I'm genuinely happy.
Akang senang banget.
Because I get to be together with you.
Karena bisa sama-sama terus sama Eneng.
Did I make things hard for you?
Eneng nyusahin hidup Akang, ya?
No.
Enggak.
When have you ever given me a hard time?
Kapan sih Eneng nyusahin Akang?
You're my everything.
Eneng teh segalanya buat Akang.
What's wrong? Too spicy?
Kenapa? Pedes banget?
It is. But it's good.
Pedes yang ini! Tapi enak.
Delicious.
Tetep enak.
If God wills,
Kalau Tuhan mengizinkan,
we must stay together.
kita harus setia, sama-sama terus.
In life and in death.
Sehidup semati, ya, Neng?
With Makmur comes Sari.
Ada Makmur, pasti ada Sari.
Where there's Sari, there's Makmur.
Ada Sari, pasti ada Makmur.
Promise?
Janji?
I promise.
Janji.
I'll be home before Cipluk is born.
Akang pulang sebelum Cipluk lahir.
I'm off.
Akang pergi, ya, Neng.
Dear God.
Ya, Tuhan.
Please let me see my wife and child.
Izinkan saya melihat anak dan istri saya.
I'm not ready to die today.
Saya belum mau mati hari ini. Saya belum mau mati.
Please let my husband see his wife and child.
Izinkan suami saya melihat istri dan anaknya.
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak.
Your prayers saved me on the battlefield.
Karena doa Eneng, Akang selamat di medan perang.
That's why I'm here today.
Makanya Akang ada di sini.
Thanks to you,
Gara-gara Eneng,
I'm no longer afraid to enter a haunted house.
Akang udah enggak takut lagi masuk ke rumah setan.
But I'm a ghost.
Tapi Eneng setan.
Aren't you scared of ghosts?
Akang kan takut sama setan, Kang.
I am.
Takut sih.
But I'm more scared of living without you.
Tapi Akang mah lebih takut kalau enggak bisa hidup sama Eneng.
I love you, Sari.
Kang Makmur cinta sama kamu, Sari.
Forever.
Selamanya.
I love you too.
Eneng juga, Kang.
I love you.
Eneng juga.
Will you let them go?
Bebasin mereka, ya, Neng?
Please.
Kasihan.
Is this weird?
Aneh enggak, Kang,
Seeing my arms do this?
lihat tangan Eneng bisa begini?
A little bit.
Aneh sih.
But I'll get used to it.
Tapi lama-lama juga Akang biasa.
In fact…
Malahan jadinya
I think it's sexy.
seksi.
Kang Mak.
Kang Mak.
Neng Sari.
Neng Sari.
Sari.
Sari.
Kang Makmur.
Kang Makmur.
Fajrul.
Fajrul.
Kang Mak!
Kang Mak!
Jaka.
Jaka.
Supra.
Supra.
Solah.
Solah.
How long should we keep calling each other?
Mau sampai kapan panggil-panggilan?
Your friends can handle being tied up till morning.
Temennya kuat kok diikat sampai pagi. Kuat.
Yeah. We may look like bacang, but we're strong enough.
Biar bentuknya kayak bacang begini, tetep kuat kita.
It's fine.
Enggak apa-apa.
Enjoy being lovey-dovey over there.
Di situ roman-romanan, deh.
We enjoy being tied up here.
Di sini iket-iketan.
Thank you, honey.
Makasih, ya, Neng.
- Mur.
- Mur.
Sorry, Mur.
Maaf, Mur.
Who's holding you?
Digendong siapa itu?
Is it Uncle Doyok?
Digendong Om Doyok, ya?
It's Uncle Fajrul.
Om Fajrul, ya.
The handsome Uncle Fajrul.
Om Fajrul ganteng.
Apparently, ghosts aren't that scary.
Tapi ternyata setan enggak seram, ya.
After all, it's Sari and Cipluk.
Ngeliat Sari, ngeliat Cipluk gitu.
Introduce us to your friends.
Mau dong, dikenalin sama teman-temannya.
I might see someone I like.
Siapa tahu ada kali.
I'd like one too.
Kalau ada sisanya, saya juga mau.
- You want one? - Do you want to see them?
- Mau juga dia. - Beneran semua mau?
- Yeah! - Sure.
- Iya! - Mau beneran.
- You have friends? - Of course.
- Emang ada? - Ada.
There.
Tuh.
Baldie.
Ayang otak…
- Baldie. - Get her!
Udah.
Give it a shot, Supra. You might like her.
Cobain dulu, Bang. Siapa tahu demen.
Go for it.
Sikat, Bang.
Mbak Yu Supi.
Mbah Yu Supi, meninggalnya kenapa?
I drowned.
Tenggelam.
You couldn't swim?
Emang enggak bisa berenang?
I can.
Bisa.
But I was drunk.
Tapi kan lagi mabok.
- No wonder her mouth reeks of garbage. - Baldie.
Pantesan bau sampah mulutnya.
Help!
Tolong!
My hair will fall out! No!
Lontong. Eh, tolong!
Slowly, be careful not to fall. It's slippery.
Pelan-pelan, ya, takut jatuh karena licin.
- Mr. San? - Mr. Mamat?
- Pak San? - Pak Mamat?
Mr. San!
Pak San!
How are you?
Bagaimana kabarmu?
I missed you!
Aku kangen!
Did you bring tourists from Thailand here?
Kamu membawa turis dari Thailand lagi?
They came all the way from Thailand
Mereka datang dari Thailand
to see this museum.
untuk melihat museum ini.
Come on in.
Masuklah!
Right now?
Sekarang?
Okay, come in everyone!
Oke. Ayo masuk, Semuanya.
- Let's take pictures! - Hello.
- Mari ambil foto! - Halo.
My honored guests. Ladies and gentlemen.
Ibu dan Bapak yang saya sayangi.
This is the legendary
Inilah rumah Kang Mak dan Sari yang sangat legendaris!
This portrait tells the story
Ini adalah potret Makmur dan Sari.
They were a couple
Mereka adalah pasangan yang terpisahkan dunia.
But by overcoming their struggles,
Walaupun begitu, dengan perjuangan,
their story becomes an inspiration
kisah mereka menjadi inspirasi
for all those in love.
bagi semua yang sedang jatuh cinta.
For all those in love.
Bagi semua yang jatuh cinta!
May our love be
Semoga cinta kita bisa kokoh dan abadi.
You may take pictures.
Silakan difoto.
Okay. Everyone, smile!
Oke. Ayo senyum, Semuanya!
One, two, three.
Satu, dua, tiga.
That was so cute! Okay.
Lucu sekali! Oke.
Let's take another one.
Mari kita ulang.
One, two, three.
Satu, dua, tiga.
Yessir!
Siap, dong!